<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The measures and offices of friendship with rules of conducting it : to which are added, two letters written to persons newly changed in their religion / by Jer. Taylor, D.D.</title>
            <title>Discourse of the nature, offices and measures of friendship</title>
            <author>Taylor, Jeremy, 1613-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41495</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355448</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355448</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64030)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1753:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The measures and offices of friendship with rules of conducting it : to which are added, two letters written to persons newly changed in their religion / by Jer. Taylor, D.D.</title>
                  <title>Discourse of the nature, offices and measures of friendship</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Jeremy, 1613-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 203, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>First published (1657) with title: A discourse of the nature, offices, and measures of friendship.</note>
                  <note>"Two letters to persons changed in their religion", p. 117-203, has half-title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Friendship.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110472:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MEASURES <hi>AND</hi> OFFICES OF <hi>FRIENDSHIP: WITH</hi> RULES of conducting it. <hi>To which are added,</hi> Two Letters written to perſons newly changed in their Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JER TAYLOR <hi>D. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Dion. Orat. 1. de Regno.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>J.G.</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton</hi> at the Angel in Ivie-lane. 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:110472:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110472:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE OF THE Nature and Offices OF <hi>FRIENDSHIP. In a Letter to the moſt Ingenious and Excellent</hi> M.K.P.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wiſe <hi>Benſirach</hi> adviſed that we ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man concerning her of whom ſhe is jealous, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110472:3"/>with a coward in matters of warre, nor with a merchant concerning exchange; and ſome other inſtances he gives of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted perſons, to whom he would not have us hearken in any matter of Counſel. For where ever the intereſt is <hi>ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> or <hi>vitious,</hi> there the bias is not on the ſide of <hi>truth</hi> or <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> becauſe <hi>theſe</hi> are ſeldome ſerv'd by profit and low re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards. But to conſult with a friend in the matters of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is like conſulting with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall perſon in Religion; they who underſtand the ſecrets of Religion, or the interior beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of friendſhip are the fitteſt to give anſwers in all inquiries concerning the reſpective ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; becauſe <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> are on the ſide of <hi>intereſt;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110472:3"/>and that which in friendſhip is moſt <hi>pleaſing</hi> and moſt <hi>uſeful,</hi> is alſo moſt <hi>reaſonable</hi> and moſt <hi>true;</hi> and a friends faireſt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt is the beſt meaſure of the conducting friendſhips: and therefore you who are ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in friendſhips could alſo have given the beſt anſwer to your own inquiries, and you could have truſted your own reaſon, becauſe it is not onely greatly inſtructed by the direct notices of things, but alſo by great experience in the matter of which you now inquire.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I will not uſe any thing that ſhall look like an excuſe, I will rather give you ſuch an account which you can eaſily reprove, then by decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your commands, ſeem more ſafe in my prudence, then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110472:4"/>open and communicative in my friendſhip to you.</p>
            <p>You firſt inquire how far a Dear and a perfect friendſhip is authoriz'd by the principles of Chriſtianity?</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer; That the word <hi>[Friendſhip]</hi> in the ſenſe we commonly mean by it, is not ſo much as named in the New-Teſtament; and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion takes no notice of it. You think it ſtrange; but read on before you ſpend ſo much as the beginning of a paſſion or a wonder upon it. There is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>[Friendſhip with the world,]</hi> and it is ſaid to be <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with God;</hi> but the word is no where elſe named, or to any other purpoſe in all the New Teſtament. It ſpeaks of Friends often; but by <hi>friends</hi> are meant
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110472:4"/>our acquaintance, or our Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, there latives of our family or our fortune, or our ſect; ſomething of ſociety, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of kindneſſe there is in it; a tenderneſſe of appellation and civility, a relation made by gifts, or by duty, by ſervices and ſubjection; and I think, I have reaſon to be confident, that the word <hi>friend</hi> (ſpeaking of humane entercourſe) is no other-wayes uſed in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels or Epiſtles, or Acts of the Apoſtles: and the reaſon of it is, the word <hi>friend</hi> is of a large ſignification; and means all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and ſocieties, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not <hi>enemy;</hi> but by <hi>friendſhips,</hi> I ſuppoſe you mean, <hi>the greateſt love, and the greateſt uſefulneſſe, and the moſt open communication, and the nobleſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110472:5"/>ſufferings, and the moſt exemplar faithfulneſſe, and the ſevereſt truth, and the heartieſt counſel, and the greateſt union of minds,</hi> of which brave men and women are capable. But then I muſt tell you that Chriſtianity hath new chriſtened it, and calls this <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> The Chriſtian knowes no enemy he hath; that is, though perſons may be injurious to him, and unworthy in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet he knowes none whom he is not firſt bound to forgive, which is indeed to make them on his part to be no ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that is, to make that the word <hi>enemy</hi> ſhal not be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to <hi>friend,</hi> it ſhall not be a relative term and ſignifie ſomething on each hand, a <hi>rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> and a <hi>correlative;</hi> and then he knows none whom he is not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110472:5"/>bound to love and pray for, to treat kindly and juſtly, liberally and obligingly. Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is Friendſhip to all the world; and when Friendſhips were the nobleſt things in the world, Charity was little, like the Sun drawn in at a chink, or his beams drawn into the centre of a Burning-glaſſe; but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity is Friendſhip, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panded like the face of the Sun when it mounts above the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern hills: and I was ſtrangely pleas'd when I ſaw ſomething of this in CICERO; for I have been ſo puſh'd at by herds and flocks of people that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low any body that whiſtles to them, or drives them to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, that I am grown afraid of any Truth that ſeems chargeable with ſingularity:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110472:6"/>but therefore I ſay, glad I was when I ſaw <hi>Laelius</hi> in <hi>Cicero</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe thus: <hi>Amicitia ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitate generis humani quam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliavit ipſa natura, contracta res eſt, &amp; adducta in anguſtum; ut omnis charitas, aut inter duos, aut inter paucos jungeretur.</hi> Nature hath made friendſhips, and ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, relations and endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and by ſomething or other we relate to all the world; there is enough in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that is willing, to make him become our friend; but when men contract friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, they incloſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and what Nature inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhould be every mans, we make proper to two or three. Friendſhip is like rivers and the ſtrand of ſeas, and the ayre, common to all the world; but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110472:6"/>Tyrants, and evil cuſtomes, wars, and want of love have made them proper and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar. But when Chriſtianity came to renew our nature, and to reſtore our lawes, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe her priviledges, and to make her aptneſſe to become religion, then it was declared that our friendſhips were to be as univerſal as our converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that is, <hi>actual</hi> to all with whom we converſe, and <hi>poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially extended</hi> unto thoſe with whom we did not. For he who was to treat his enemies with forgiveneſſe and prayers, and love and beneficence was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to have no enemies, and to have all friends.</p>
            <p>So that to your queſtion, how far a Dear and perfect friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is authoriz'd by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110472:7"/>of Chriſtianity? The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is ready and eaſie. It is warranted to extend to all Mankind; and the more we love, the better we are, and the greater our friendſhips are, the dearer we are to God; let them be as Dear, and let them be as perfect, and let them be as many as you can; there is no danger in it; onely where the reſtraint begins, there begins our imperfection; it is not ill that you entertain brave friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and worthy ſocieties: it were well if you could <hi>love,</hi> and if you could <hi>benefit</hi> all Mankind; for I conceive that is the ſumme of all friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe this is not to be expected of us in this world; but as all our graces here are but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110472:7"/>imperfect, that is, at the beſt they are but tendencies to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſo our friendſhips are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect too, and but beginnings of a celeſtial friendſhip, by which we ſhall love every one as much as they can be loved. But then ſo we muſt here <hi>in our proportion;</hi> and indeed that is it that can make the difference; we muſt be friends to all: That is, apt to doe good, loving them really, and doing to them all the benefits which we can, and which they are capable of. The Friendſhip is equall to all the World, and of it ſelfe hath no difference; but is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferenced onely by accidents, and by the capacity or inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of them that receive it. <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> are the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110472:8"/>
               <hi>bands</hi> of friendſhips; <hi>excellency</hi> and <hi>uſefulneſſe</hi> are its great <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearments: ſociety</hi> and <hi>neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> that is, the poſſibilities and the circumſtances of converſe are the <hi>determinations</hi> and <hi>actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alities</hi> of it. Now when men either are unnatural, or irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they <hi>will not</hi> be friends; when they are neither excellent nor uſeful, <hi>they are not worthy</hi> to be friends; when they are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or unknown, they <hi>cannot be friends</hi> actually and practically; but yet, as any man hath any thing of the good, contrary to thoſe evils, ſo he can have and muſt have his ſhare of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. For thus the Sun is the eye of the world; and he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to the Negro, or the cold Ruſſian, to them that dwel under the line, and them that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110472:8"/>ſtand near the Tropicks, the ſcalded Indian, or the poor boy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat ſhakes at the foot of the Riphean hills; but the fluxures of the heaven and the earth, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onveniency of abode, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pproches to the North or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>outh reſpectively change the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>manations of his beams; not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they doe not paſſe alwaies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom him, but that they are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>qually received below, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y periods and changes, by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e inlets and reflections, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceive what they can; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome have onely a dark day and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> long night from him, ſnowes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd white cattel, a miſerable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fe, and a perpetual harveſt of Catarrhes and conſumptions; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poplexies and dead palſies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut ſome have ſplendid fires, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aromatick ſpices, rich wines,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110472:9"/>and well digeſted fruits, great wit and great courage; becauſe they dwell in his eye, and look in his face, and are the Courtiers of the Sun, and wait upon him in his Chambers of the Eaſt; juſt ſo is it in friendſhips: ſome are worthy, and ſome are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; ſome dwell hard by and are fitted for converſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Nature joyns ſome to us, and Religion combines us with o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers; ſociety and accidents parity of fortune, and equal di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſitions do actuate our friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips: which of themſelves and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their prime diſpoſition are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for all Mankind according as any one can receive them We ſee this beſt exemplified b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two inſtances and expreſſions o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> friendſhips and charity: <hi>viz. Almes</hi> and <hi>Prayers;</hi> Every on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110472:9"/>that needs relief is equally the object of our charity; but though to all mankind in equal needs we ought to be alike in charity; yet we ſignifie this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally and by limits, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct meaſures: the poor man that is near me, he whom I meet, he whom I love, he whom I fancy, he who did me benefit, he who relates to my family, he rather then another, becauſe my expreſſions being finite and narrow, and cannot extend to all in equal ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, muſt be appropriate to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe whoſe circumſtances beſt it me: and yet even to all I give my almes: to all the world that needs them; I pray for all mankind, I am grieved at every ſad ſtory I hear; I am troubled when I hear of a pretty Bride
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110472:10"/>murdered in her bride-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber by an ambitious and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd Rval; I ſhed a tear when I am told that a brave King was miſ-underſtood, then ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then impriſoned, and then put to death by evil men: and I can never read the ſtory of the Pariſian Maſſacre, or the Sicili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Veſpers, but my blood cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and I am diſorder'd by two or three affections. A good man is a friend to all the world; and he is not truly charitable that does not wiſh well, and do good to all mankind in what he can; but though we muſt pray for all men, yet we ſay ſpeciall Letanies for brave Kings and holy Prelates, and the wiſe Guides of ſouls; for our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Relations, our Wives and Children.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:110472:10"/>
            <p>The effect of this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion is, that the Univerſall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riendſhip of which I ſpeak, muſt be <hi>limited,</hi> becauſe <hi>we are ſo:</hi> In thoſe things where we ſtand next to immenſity and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity, as in good wiſhes and prayers, and a <hi>readineſſe</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit all mankind, in theſe our friendſhips muſt not be limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but in other things which paſſe under our hand and eye, our voices and our material ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes; our hands can reach no further but to our arms end, and our voices can but ſound till the next air be quiet, and therefore they can have enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe but within the ſphere of their own activity; our needs and our converſations are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by a few, and they cannot reach to all; where they can,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110472:11"/>they muſt; but <hi>where it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible it cannot be neceſſary.</hi> It muſt therefore follow, that ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> friendſhips to mankind may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit variety as does our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; and as by nature we ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made <hi>ſociable</hi> to all, ſo we are <hi>friendly;</hi> but as all cannot actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally be of our ſociety, ſo neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can all be admitted to a ſpecial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> actuall friendſhip; Of <hi>ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſes</hi> all men are capable but <hi>not of all;</hi> Men can pray for one another, and abſtai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from doing injuries to all the world, and be deſirous to doe all mankind good, and love all men; Now this friendſhip we muſt pay to all becauſe we can but if we can do no more to all we muſt ſhew our readineſſe to do more good to all by actually doing more good to all them to whom we can.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:110472:11"/>
            <p>To ſome we can, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there are nearer friendſhips to ſome then to others, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as there are natural or civil nearneſſes, relations and ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and as I cannot expreſſe my friendſhips to all in equall meaſures and ſignifications, that is, as I cannot doe benefits to all alike: ſo neither am I tied to love all alike: for although there is much reaſon to love every man; yet there are more reaſons to love ſome then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and if I muſt love becauſe there is reaſon I ſhould; then I muſt <hi>love more,</hi> where there is <hi>more reaſon;</hi> and where ther's a ſpecial affection &amp; a great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to doe good and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in certain perſons towards each other, there is that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall charity and indearment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110472:12"/>which Philoſophy calls <hi>friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips;</hi> but our Religion calls <hi>love</hi> or <hi>charity.</hi> Now if the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry be concerning this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall friendſhip. 1. <hi>how it can be appropriate,</hi> that is, who to be choſen to it; 2. <hi>how far it may extend;</hi> that is, with what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions ſignified; 3. <hi>how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted?</hi> The anſwers will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon ſuch conſiderations which will be neither uſeleſſe nor unpleaſant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There may be a ſpeciall friendſhip contracted for any ſpeciall excellency whatſoever; becauſe <hi>friendſhips are nothing but love and ſociety mixt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> that is, <hi>a converſing with them whom we love;</hi> now for whatſoever we can love any one, for that we can be his friend; and ſince every excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110472:12"/>is a degree of amability, every ſuch worthineſſe is a juſt and proper motive of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or loving converſation. But yet in theſe things there is an order and proportion. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Good man is the beſt friend, and therefore ſooneſt to be choſen, longer to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd; and indeed never to be parted with, unleſſe he ceaſe to be that for which he was choſen.
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where vertue dwells there friendſhips make,</l>
                     <l>But evill neighbourhoods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:110472:13"/>But although vertue alone is the worthieſt cauſe of amabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and can weigh down any one conſideration; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to a man that is vertuous every man ought to be a friend; yet I doe not meane the ſevere, and philoſophicall excellencies of ſome moroſe perſons who are indeed wiſe unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and exemplar to others: by <hi>vertue</hi> here I doe not meane <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>temperance, charity</hi> and <hi>devotion;</hi> for theſe I am to love the man, but friendſhip is ſomething more then that: <hi>Friendſhip is the neareſt love and the neareſt ſociety</hi> of which the perſons are capable: Now juſtice is a good entercourſe for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, as all men are that buy and ſell; and temperance makes a Man good company,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110472:13"/>and helps to make a wiſe man; but a perfect friendſhip requires ſomething elſe, theſe muſt be in him that is choſen to be my friend; but for theſe I doe not make him my <hi>privado;</hi> that is, my ſpeciall and peculiar friend: but if he be <hi>a good man,</hi> then he is properly fitted to be my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relative in the nobleſt combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>And for this we have the beſt warrant in the world: <hi>For a juſt man ſcarcely will a man die;</hi> the Syriac interpreter reads it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for an unjuſt man ſcarcely will a man die;</hi> that is, a wicked man is at no hand fit to receive the expreſſion of the greateſt friendſhip; but all the Greek copies that ever I ſaw, or read of, read it as we doe; <hi>for a righteous man or a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110472:14"/>juſt man,</hi> that is, juſtice and righteouſneſſe is not the neareſt indearment of friendſhip; but for <hi>a good man</hi> ſome will even dare to die: that is, for a man that is ſweetly diſpoſed, ready to doe acts of goodneſſe and to oblige others, to doe things uſefull and profitable, for a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man, a beneficent, bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, one who delights in doing good to his friend, ſuch a man may have the higheſt friendſhip; he may have a friend that will die for him. And this is the meaning of <hi>Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius:</hi> Vertue may be deſpiſed, ſo may Learning and Nobility; <hi>at una eſt amicitia in rebus hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manis de cujus utilitatc omnes conſentiunt:</hi> onely friendſhip is that thing, which becauſe all know to be uſefull and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110472:14"/>no man can deſpiſe; that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, goodneſſe or beneficence makes friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips. For if he be a good man he will love where he is belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and that's the firſt tie of friendſhip.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>That was the commendation of the braveſt friendſhip in <hi>Theocritus,</hi>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They lov'd each other with a love</l>
                     <l>That did in all things equal prove.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>—<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The world was under Saturns reign</l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110472:15"/>
                     <l>When he that lov'd was lov'd again.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> For it is impoſſible this neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of friendſhip can be where there is not mutuall love; but this is ſecured if I chooſe a good man; for he that is apt enough to begin alone, will never be behind in the relation and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency; and therefore I like the Gentiles Letany well.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let God give friends to me for my reward,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall my love with equal love regard;</l>
                  <l>Happy are they, who when
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110472:15"/>they give their heart.</l>
                  <l>Find ſuch as in exchange their own impart.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>But there is more in it then this felicity amounts to. For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the good man</hi> is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, uſefull perſon, and that's the band of an effective friendſhip. For I doe not think that friendſhips are Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical nothings, created for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, or that men or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould ſtare upon each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers faces, and make dialogues of newes and prettineſſes, and look babies in one anothers eyes. Friendſhip is the allay of our ſorrowes, the eaſe of our paſſions, the diſcharge of our oppreſſions, the ſanctuary to our calamities, the counſellour of our doubts, the clarity of our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110472:16"/>minds, the emiſſion of our thoughts, the exerciſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of what we medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate: And although I love my friend becauſe he is worthy, yet he is not worthy if he can doe no good. I doe not ſpeak of accidentall hinderances and misfortunes by which the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt man may become unable to help his Child; but of the naturall and artificiall capacities of the man. He onely is fit to be choſen for a friend, who can doe thoſe offices for which friendſhip is excellent. For (miſtake not) no man can be loved for himſelf; our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in this world cannot reach ſo high; it is well if we would love God at that rate, and I very much fear, that if God did us no good, we might
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110472:16"/>admire his Beauties, but we ſhould have but a ſmall propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of love towards him; and therefore it is, that God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear <hi>the obedience,</hi> that is, <hi>the love</hi> of his ſervants, ſignifies what benefits he gives us, what great good things he does for us. <hi>I am the Lord God that brought thee out of the land of Egypt:</hi> and <hi>does Job ſerve God for nought?</hi> and <hi>he that comes to God, muſt believe that he is, and that he is a rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> all his other greatneſſes are objects of fear and wonder, it is his goodneſſe that makes him lovely: and ſo it is in friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips. He onely is fit to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for a friend who can give me counſel, or defend my cauſe, or guide me right, or relieve my need, or can and will, when I need it, doe me good: onely
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110472:17"/>this I adde: into the heaps of doing good, I will reckon <hi>[lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me]</hi> for it is a pleaſure to be bloved; but when his love ſignifies nothing but kiſſing my cheek, or talking kindly, and and can goe no further, it is a proſtitution of the bravery of friendſhip to ſpend it upon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent people who are (it may be) loads to their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, but can never eaſe my loads: but my friend is a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy perſon when he can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to me inſtead of God, a guide or a ſupport, an eye, or a hand; a ſtaffe, or a rule: There muſt be in friendſhip ſomething to diſtinguiſh it from a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and a Countryman, from a School-fellow or a Goſſip, from a Sweet-heart or a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-traveller: Friendſhip may
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110472:17"/>look in at any one of theſe doors, but it ſtayes not any where til it come to be the beſt thing in the world: and when we conſider that one man is not better then another, neither to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God nor Man, but by doing better and braver things, we ſhall alſo ſee, that that which is moſt beneficent is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo moſt excellent; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe friendſhips muſt needs be moſt perfect, where the friends can be moſt uſeful. For men cannot be uſeful but by worthineſſes in the ſeveral inſtances: a fool cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed upon for counſel; nor a vitious perſon for the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of vertue, nor a beggar for relief, nor a ſtranger for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, nor a tatler to keep a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, nor a pittileſs perſon truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110472:18"/>with my complaint, nor a covetous man with my childes fortune, nor a falſe perſon without a witneſſe, nor a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious perſon with a private deſign; nor him that I fear with the treaſures of my love: But he that is wiſe and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, rich and at hand, cloſe and mercifull, free of his money and tenacious of a ſecret, open and ingenuous, true and honeſt, is of himſelf an excellent man; and therefore fit to be lov'd; and he can do good to me in all capacities where I can need him, and therefore is fit to be a friend. I confeſſe we are forced in our friendſhips to abate ſome of theſe ingredients; but full meaſures of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, would have full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of worthineſſe; and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110472:18"/>according as any defect is in the foundation; in the relation alſo there may be imperfection: and indeed I ſhall not blame the friendſhip ſo it be worthy, though it be not perfect; not onely becauſe friendſhip is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which cannot be perfect here, but becauſe there is not in the world a perfect cauſe of perfect friendſhip.</p>
            <p>If you can ſuſpect that this diſcourſe can ſuppoſe friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be mercenary, and to be defective in the greateſt worthineſſe of it, which is to love our friend for our friends ſake, I ſhall eaſily be able to defend my ſelf; becauſe I ſpeak of the election and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of chooſing friends: after he is choſen do as nobly as you talke, and love as purely as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110472:19"/>you dream, and let your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation be as metaphyſical as your diſcourſe, and proceed in this method, till you be confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by experience; yet till then, the caſe is otherwiſe when we ſpeak of chooſing one to be my friend: He is not my friend till I have choſen him, or loved him; and if any man enquires whom he ſhall chooſe or whom he ſhould love, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ought not to be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that we ſhould love him who hath leaſt amability; that we ſhould chooſe him who hath leaſt reaſon to be choſen: But if it be anſwered, he is to be choſen to be my friend who is moſt worthy in himſelf, not he that can do moſt good to me; I ſay, here is a diſtinction but no difference; for he is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110472:19"/>moſt worthy in himſelf who can do moſt good; and if he can love me too, that is, if he will do me all the good he can, that I need, then he is my friend and he deſerves it. And it is impoſſible from a friend to ſeparate a will to do me good: and therefore I do not chooſe well, if I chooſe one that hath not power; for if it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with the nobleneſſe of friendſhip to deſire that my friend be ready to do me bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or ſupport, it is not ſenſe to ſay, is is ignoble to deſire he ſhould really do it when I need; and if it were not for pleaſure or profit, we might as well be without a friend as have him.</p>
            <p>Among all the pleaſures and profits, the <hi>ſenſual pleaſure</hi> and the <hi>matter of money</hi> are the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110472:20"/>loweſt and the leaſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although they may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be uſed in friendſhip, and ſo not wholly excluded from the conſideration of him that is to chooſe, yet of all things they are to be the leaſt regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>When fortune frowns upon a man,</l>
               <l>A friend does more then mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney can.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For there are beſides theſe, many profits and many plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and becauſe theſe onely are ſordid, all the other are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and fair, and the expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them no diſparagements to the beſt friendſhips. For can
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110472:20"/>any wiſe or good man be angry if I ſay, I chooſe this man to be my friend, becauſe he is able to give me counſell, to reſtrain my wandrings, to comfort me in my ſorrows; he is pleaſant to me in private, and uſefull in publick; he will make my joyes double, and divide my grief between himſelf and me? For what elſe ſhould I chooſe? For being a fool, and uſeleſſe; for a pretty face or a ſmooth chin; I confeſſe it is poſſible to be a friend to one that is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and pitiable, handſome and good for nothing, that eats well, and drinks deep: but he cannot be a friend to me; and I love him with a fondneſſe or a pity, but it cannot be a noble friendſhip.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:110472:21"/>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſaid <hi>Menander.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>By wine and mirth and every dayes delight</l>
                  <l>We chooſe our friends, to whom we think we might</l>
                  <l>Our ſouls intruſt; but fools are they that lend</l>
                  <l>Their boſome to the ſhadow of a friend.</l>
               </lg> 
            </q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> calls ſuch friendſhips, the Idols and Images of friendſhip. True and brave friendſhips are between worthy perſons; and there is in Mankind no degree
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110472:21"/>of worthineſſe, but is alſo a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of uſefulneſſe, and by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing by which a man is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, I may be profited: and becauſe thoſe are the braveſt friends which can beſt ſerve the ends of friendſhips, either we muſt ſuppoſe that friendſhips are not the greateſt comforts in the world, or elſe we muſt ſay, he chooſes his friend beſt, that chooſes ſuch a one by whom he can receive the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt comforts and aſſiſtances.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This being the meaſure of all friendſhips; they all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of excellency, according as they are fitted to this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: a friend may be counſelled well enough though his friend be not the wiſeſt man in the world, and he may be pleaſed in his ſociety though he be not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110472:22"/>the beſt natured man in the world; but ſtill it muſt be, that ſomething excellent is, or is apprehended, or elſe it can be no worthy friendſhip; becauſe the choice is imprudent and fooliſh. Chooſe for your friend him that is wiſe and good, and ſecret and juſt, ingenuous and honeſt; and in thoſe things which have a latitude, uſe your own liberty; but in ſuch things which conſiſt in an indiviſible point, make no abatements: That is, you muſt not chooſe him to be your friend that is not honeſt and ſecret, juſt and true to a tittle; but if he be wiſe at all, and uſefull in any degree, and as good as you can have him, you need not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to own your friendſhips; though ſometimes you may be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110472:22"/>aſhamed of ſome imperfections of your friend.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But if you yet enquire further, whether fancy may be an ingredient in your choice? I anſwer, that fancy may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to this as to all other actions in which there is a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and variety; and we ſhall find that there may be pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarities and little partialities, a <hi>friendſhip, improperly ſo called,</hi> entring upon accounts of an innocent paſſion and a pleas'd fancy; even our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf loved Saint <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> by a ſpeciall love, which was ſignified by ſpecial treatments; and of the young man that ſpake well and wiſely to Chriſt, it is affirmed, <hi>Jeſus loved him:</hi> that is, he fancied the man, and his ſoul had a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110472:23"/>cognation and ſimilitude of temper and inclination. For in all things where there is a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, every faculty will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be pleaſed, and ſometimes the meaneſt perſons in a houſe have a feſtival; even ſympathies and naturall incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to ſome perſons, and a conformity of humours, and proportionable loves, and the beauty of the face, and a witty anſwer may firſt ſtrike the flint and kindle a ſpark, which if it falls upon tender and compliant natures may grow into a flame; but this will never be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de at the rate of friendſhip, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be fed by pure materials, by <hi>worthineſſes</hi> which <hi>are the food of friendſhip:</hi> where thſe are not, men and women may be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with one anothers compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110472:23"/>and lie under the ſame roof, and make themſelves companions of equall proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and humour their friend; but if you call this friendſhip, you give a ſacred name to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour or fancy; for there is a Platonic friendſhip as well as a Platonic love; but they being but the Images of more noble bodies are but like tinſell dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which will ſhew bravely by candle-light, and do excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently in a mask, but are not fit for converſation, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial entercourſes of our life. Theſe are the prettineſſes of proſperity and good natured wit; but when we ſpeak of friendſhip, which is the beſt thing in the world (for it is love and beneficence; it is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that is fitted for ſociety)
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110472:24"/>we cannot ſuppoſe a brave pile ſhould be built up with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and they that build Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the aire, and look upon friendſhip, as upon a fine Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, a thing that pleaſes the fancy, but is good for nothing elſe, will do well when they are aſleep, or when they are come to Elyſium; and for ought I know in the mean time may be as much in love with <hi>Mandana</hi> in the <hi>Grand Cyrus,</hi> as with the <hi>Infanta of Spain,</hi> or any of the moſt perfect beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and real excellencies of the world: and by dreaming of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and abſtracted friendſhips, make them ſo immateriall that they periſh in the handling and become good for nothing.</p>
            <p>But I know not whither I was going; I did onely mean
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110472:24"/>to ſay that becauſe friendſhip is that by which the world is moſt bleſſed and receives moſt good, it ought to be choſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the worthieſt perſons, that is, amongſt thoſe that can doe greateſt benefit to each other; and though in equal wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe I may chooſe by my eye, or ear, that is, into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the eſſential I may take in alſo the accidental and extrinſick worthineſſes; yet I ought to give every one their juſt value; when the internal beauties are equal, theſe ſhall help to weigh down the ſcale, and I will love a worthy friend that can delight me as well as profit me, rather then him who cannot delight me at all, and profit me <hi>no more;</hi> but yet I will not weigh the gayeſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110472:25"/>flowers, or the wings of butter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flies againſt wheat; but when I am to chooſe wheat, I may take that which looks the brighteſt; I had rather ſee Thyme and Roſes, Marjoram and July<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowers that are fair and ſweet and medicinal, then the pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt Tulips that are good for nothing: And my Sheep and Kine are better ſervants then Race-horſes and Greyhounds: And I ſhall rather furniſh my Study with <hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Cicero,</hi> with <hi>Livy</hi> and <hi>Polybius,</hi> then with <hi>Caſſandra</hi> &amp; <hi>Ibrahim Baſſa;</hi> and if I doe give an houre to theſe for divertiſement or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet I will dwell with them that can inſtruct me, and make me wiſe and eloquent, ſevere and uſefull to my ſelf &amp; others. I end this with the ſaying of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110472:25"/>
               <hi>Laelius</hi> in <hi>Cicero: Amicitia non debet conſequi utilitatem, ſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micitiam utilitas.</hi> When I chooſe my friend, I wil not ſtay till I have received a kindneſſe; but I will chooſe ſuch an one that can doe me many if I need them: But I mean ſuch kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes which make me wiſer, and which make me better; that is, I will when I chooſe my friend, chooſe him that is the braveſt, the worthieſt and the moſt excellent perſon: and then your firſt Queſtion is ſoon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; to love ſuch a perſon and to contract ſuch friendſhips is juſt ſo authorized by the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtianity, as it is warranted to love wiſdome and vertue, goodneſs &amp; beneficence, and all the impreſſes of God upon the ſpirits of brave men.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:110472:26"/>
            <p n="2">2. The next inquiry is <hi>how far it may extend?</hi> That is, by what expreſſions it may be ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified? I find that <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> loved at a ſtrange rate; they were both good men; though it happened that <hi>Jonathan</hi> was on the obliging ſide; but here the expreſſions were; <hi>Jonathan</hi> watched for <hi>Davids</hi> good; told him of his danger, and helped him to eſcape; took part with <hi>Davids</hi> innocence againſt his Fathers malice and injuſtice; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all this, did it to his own prejudice; and they two ſtood like two feet ſupporting one body; though <hi>Jonathan</hi> knew that <hi>David</hi> would prove like the foot of a Wreſtler, and would ſupplant him, not by any unworthy or unfriendly action,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110472:26"/>but it was from God; and he gave him his hand to ſet him upon his own throne.</p>
            <p>We find his parallels in the Gentile ſtories: young <hi>Atheno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> having divided the eſtate with his Brother <hi>Xenon;</hi> divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it again when <hi>Xenon</hi> had ſpent his own ſhare; and <hi>Lucul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> would not take the Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip till his younger brother had firſt enjoyed it for a year; but <hi>Pollux</hi> divided with <hi>Caſtor</hi> his immortality; and you know who offer'd himſelf to death being pledge for his friend; and his friend by performing his word reſcued him as brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and when we find in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that <hi>for a good man ſome will even dare to die;</hi> and that <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> laid their necks down for S. <hi>Paul;</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110472:27"/>the <hi>Galatians</hi> would have given him their very eyes, that is, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that was moſt dear to them, and ſome others were neer unto death for his ſake; and that it is a precept of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity, to lay down our lives for our brethren, that is, thoſe who were combined in a cauſe of Religion, who were u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited with the ſame hopes, and imparted to each other ready aſſiſtances, and grew dear by common ſufferings, we need enquire no further for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of friendſhips: <hi>Greater love then this hath no man, then that he lay down his life for his friends;</hi> and this we are oblig'd to do in ſome Caſes for all Chriſtians; and therefore we may doe it for thoſe who are to us in this preſent and imperfect
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110472:27"/>ſtate of things, that which all the good men and women in the world ſhall be in Heaven, that is, in the ſtate of perfect friendſhips. This is the biggeſt; but then it includes and can ſuppoſe all the reſt; and if this may be done for all, and in ſome caſes muſt for any one of the multitude, we need not ſcruple whether we may doe it for thoſe who are better then a multitude. But as for the thing it ſelf, it is not eaſily and lightly to be done; and a man muſt not die for humour, nor expend ſo great a Jewel for a trifle: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſaid <hi>Philo;</hi> we will hardly die when it is for nothing, when no good, no worthy end is ſerved, and become a Sacrifice to redeem a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110472:28"/>foot-boy. But we may not give our life to redeem another: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe 1. The party for whom we die be a worthy and an uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful perſon; better for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, or better for Religion, and more uſeful to others then my ſelf. Thus <hi>Ribiſchius</hi> the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man died bravely when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Sacrifice for his Maſter, <hi>Maurice</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony;</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering his Maſters body with his own, that he might eſcape the furie of the Turkiſh Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. <hi>Succurram perituro, ſed ut ipſe non peream, niſi ſi futurus ero magni hominis, aut magnae rei merces,</hi> ſaid <hi>Seneca.</hi> I will help a dying perſon if I can; but I will not die my ſelf for him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe by my death I ſave a brave man, or become the price of a great thing; that is, I will die
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:110472:28"/>for a Prince, for the republick, or to ſave an Army, as <hi>David</hi> expos'd himſelf to combat with the Philiſtin for the redemption of the hoſt of Iſrael: and in this ſenſe, that is true; <hi>Praeſtat ut pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reat unus, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Unitas,</hi> better that <hi>one</hi> periſh then a <hi>multitude.</hi> 2. A man dies bravely when he gives his temporall life to ſave the ſoul of any ſingle perſon in the Chriſtian world. It is a worthy exchange, &amp; the glorification of that love by which Chriſt gave his life for every ſoul. Thus he that reproves an erring Prince wiſely and neceſſarily, he that affirms a fundamental truth, or ſtands up for the glory of the Divine attributes, though he die for it, becomes a worthy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. 3. Theſe are duty, but it may be heroick and full of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110472:29"/>Chriſtian bravery, to give my life to reſcue a noble and a brave friend; though I my ſelf be as worthy a man as he; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the preference of him is an act of humility in me; and of friendſhip towards him; <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> making a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous difference where <hi>art</hi> and <hi>nature</hi> have made all equall.</p>
            <p>Some have fancied other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of treating our friends. One ſort of men ſay that we are to expect that our friends ſhould value us as we value our ſelves: which if it were to be admitted, will require that we make no friendſhips with a proud man; and ſo far indeed were well; but then this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion does exclude ſome humble men who are moſt to be valued, and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110472:29"/>they undervalue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Others ſay that a friend is to value his friend as much as his friend values him; but neither is this well or ſafe, wiſe or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient; for it makes friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a meer bargaine, and is ſomething like the Countrey weddings in ſome places where I have been; where the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom and the bride muſt meet in the half way, and if they fail a ſtep, they retire and break the match: It is not good to make a reckoning in friendſhip; that's merchandiſe, or it may be gratitude, but not noble friendſhip; in which each part ſtrives to out-do the other in ſignifications of an excellent love: And <hi>amongst true friends there is no fear of loſing any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:110472:30"/>
            <p>But that which amongſt the old Philoſophers comes nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the right, is that we love our friends as we love our ſelves. If they had meant it as our Bleſſed Saviour did, of that generall friendſhip by which we are to love all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, it had been perfect and well; or if they had meant it of the inward affection, or of outward juſtice; but becauſe they meant it of the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent friendſhips, and of the outward ſignifications of it, it cannot be ſufficient: for a friend may and muſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times do more for his friend then he would do for himſelf. Some men will periſh before they will begge or petition for themſelves to ſome certaine perſons; but they account it
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:110472:30"/>noble to do it for their friend, and they will want rather then their friend ſhall want; and they will be more earneſt in praiſe or diſpraiſe reſpectively for their friend then for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And indeed I account <hi>that</hi> one of the greateſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of reall friendſhip is, that a friend can really endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to have his friend advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in honour, in reputation, in the opinion of wit or learning before himſelf.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurum &amp; opes, <note place="margin">Martial. l. 8. ep. 18.</note> &amp; rura frequens donabit amicus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui velit ingenio cedere rarus erit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed tibi tantus ineſt veteris reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus amici,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carior ut mea ſit quam tua fama tibi.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:110472:31"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lands, gold and trifles many give or lend;</l>
                  <l>But he that ſtoops in fame is a rare friend:</l>
                  <l>In friendſhips orbe thou art the brighteſt ſtar,</l>
                  <l>Before thy fame mine thou preferreſt far.</l>
               </lg> 
            </q>
            <p>But then be pleaſed to think that therefore I ſo highly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue this ſignification of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, becauſe I ſo highly value humility. Humility and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity are the two greateſt graces in the world; and theſe are the greateſt ingredients which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute friendſhip and expreſſe it.</p>
            <p>But there needs no other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of friendſhip, but that it may be as great as you can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110472:31"/>it; beyond death it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go, to death it may, when the cauſe is reaſonable and juſt, charitable and religious: and yet if there be any thing great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then to ſuffer death (and pain and ſhame to ſome are more inſufferable) a true and noble friendſhip ſhrinks not at the greateſt trials.</p>
            <p>And yet there is a limit even to friendſhip. It muſt be as great as our friend fairly needs in all things where we are not tied up by a former duty, to God, to our ſelves, or ſome pre-obliging relative. When <hi>Pollux</hi> heard ſomebody whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper a reproch againſt his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Caſtor,</hi> he killed the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer with his fiſt: that was a zeal which his friendſhip could not warrant. <hi>Nulla eſt excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110472:32"/>ſi amici cauſâ peccaveris,</hi> ſaid <hi>Cicero.</hi> No friendſhip can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe a ſin: And this the braver Romans inſtanced in the matter of duty to their Countrey. It is not lawful to fight on our friends part againſt our Prince or Countrey; and therefore when <hi>Caius Bloſius</hi> of <hi>Cuma</hi> in the ſedition of <hi>Gracchus</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt his Countrey, when he was taken he anſwered, that he loved <hi>Tiberius Gracchus</hi> ſo dearly, that he thought fit to follow him whitherſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he led; and begg'd par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don upon that account. They who were his Judges were ſo noble, that though they knew it no fair excuſe: yet for the honour of friendſhip they did not directly reject his motion: but put him to death, becauſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110472:32"/>he did not follow, but led on <hi>Gracchus,</hi> and brought his friend into the ſnare: For ſo they preſerved the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of friendſhip on either hand, by neither ſuffering it to be ſullied by a foul excuſe, nor yet rejected in any fair pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. A man may not be perjured for his friend. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to have read in the Hiſtory of the Low-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes, that <hi>Grimſton</hi> and <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> when <hi>Bergenapzoom</hi> was beſieged by the Duke of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> acted for the intereſt of the Qu: of <hi>Englands</hi> forces a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſign; but being ſuſpected and put for their acquittance to take the Sacrament of the Altar, they diſſembled their perſons, and their intereſt, their deſign &amp; their religion, and did
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110472:33"/>for the Queens ſervice (as one wittily wrote to her) give not onely their bodies but their ſouls, and ſo deſerved a reward greater then ſhe could pay them: I cannot ſay this is a thing greater then a friendſhip can require, for it is not great at all, but a great villany, which hath no name, and no order in worthy entercourſes; and no obligation to a friend can reach as high as our duty to God: And he that does a baſe thing in zeal for his friend, burns the golden thred that ties their hearts together; it is a <hi>conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy,</hi> but no longer <hi>friendſhip.</hi> And when <hi>Cato</hi> lent his wife to <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> lent his to a merry Greek, they could not amongſt wiſe perſons ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſo much as the fame of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110472:33"/>worthy friends, neither could thoſe great Names legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate an unworthy action un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the moſt plauſible title.</p>
            <p>It is certain that amongſt friends their eſtates are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; that is, by whatſoever I can reſcue my friend from ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, I am to ſerve him, or not to call him friend; there is a great latitude in this, and it is to be reſtrained by no pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but when there is on the other ſide a great neceſſity nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vitious nor avoidable: A man may chooſe whether he will or no; and he does not ſin in not doing it, unleſs he have bound himſelf to it: <hi>But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly friendſhip is the greateſt band in the world,</hi> and if he have profeſſed a great friendſhip, he hath a very great obligation
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110472:34"/>to doe that and more; and he can no wayes be diſobliged but by the care of his Naturall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</p>
            <p>I ſaid, <hi>[Friendſhip is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bond in the world,]</hi> and I had reaſon for it, for it is all the bands that this world hath; and there is no ſociety, and there is no relation that is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, but it is made ſo by the communications of friendſhip, and by partaking ſome of its excellencies. For friendſhip is a tranſcendent, and ſignifies as much as <hi>Unity</hi> can meane, and every conſent, and every plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and every benefit, and every ſociety is the Mother or the Daughter of friendſhip. Some friendſhips are made by <hi>nature,</hi> ſome by <hi>contract,</hi> ſome by <hi>intereſt,</hi> and ſome by <hi>ſouls.</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:110472:34"/>And in proportion to theſe wayes of Uniting, ſo the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips are greater or leſſe, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous or naturall, profitable or holy, or all this together. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture makes excellent friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, of which we obſerve ſomething in ſocial plants; growing better in each others neighbourhood then where they ſtand ſingly: And in ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals it is more notorious, whoſe friendſhips extend ſo far as to herd and dwell together, to play, and feed, to defend and fight for one another, and to cry in abſence, and to rejoyce in one anothers preſence. But theſe friendſhips have other names leſſe noble, they are <hi>ſympathy,</hi> or they are <hi>inſtinct.</hi> But if to this naturall friendſhip there be reaſon ſuperadded,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110472:35"/>ſomething will come in upon the ſtock of reaſon which will ennoble it but becauſe no Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers can riſe higher then Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, reaſon ſhall draw out all the diſpoſitions which are in Nature and eſtabliſh them into friendſhips, but they cannot ſurmount the communications of Nature; Nature can make no friendſhips greater then her own excellencies. Nature is the way of contracting neceſſary friendſhips: that is, by nature ſuch friendſhips are contracted without which we cannot live, and be educated, or be well, or be at all. In this ſcene, that of Parents and Children is the greateſt, which indeed is begun in nature, but is actuated by ſociety and mutuall endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For Parents love their
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110472:35"/>Children becauſe they love themſelves, Children being but like emiſſions of water, ſymbolicall, or indeed the ſame with the fountaine; and they in their poſterity ſee the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and inſtruments of a civil immortality; but if Parents and Children do not live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we ſee their friendſhips and their loves are much aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſupported onely by fame and duty, by cuſtomes and religion, which to nature are but artificial pillars, and make this friendſhip to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated, and to paſſe from its own kind to another. That of Children to their Parents is not properly friendſhip, but gratitude and intereſt, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and whatever can ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene of the nature of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110472:36"/>comes in upon another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; upon ſociety and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and choice.</p>
            <p>This relation on either hand makes great Dearneſſes: But it hath ſpeciall and proper ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications of it, and there is a ſpeciall duty incumbent on each other reſpectively. This friendſhip and ſocial relation is not equall, and there is too much authority on one ſide, and too much fear on the other to make equal friendſhips; and therefore although this is one of the kinds of friendſhip, that is of a ſocial and relative love and converſation, yet in the more proper uſe of the word; [Friendſhip] does doe ſome things which Father and Son doe not; I inſtance in the free and open communicating coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110472:36"/>and the evenneſſe and pleaſantneſſe of converſation; and conſequently the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the paternal and filial love as they are divers in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and unequal, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another kind of friendſhip then we meane in our inquiry; ſo they are ſuch a duty which no other friendſhip can annul: becauſe their mutual duty is bound upon them by religion long before any other friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips can be contracted; and therefore having firſt poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt abide for ever. The duty and love to Parents muſt not yeild to religion, much leſſe to any new friendſhips: and our Parents are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the Corban; and are at no hand to be laid aſide but when they engage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110472:37"/>againſt God: That is, in the rights which this relation and kind of friendſhip challenges as its propriety, it is ſupreme and cannot give place to any other friendſhips; till the Father gives his right away, and God or the Lawes conſent to it; as in the caſe of marriage, eman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation, and adoption to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther family: in which caſes though love and gratitude are ſtill obliging, yet the ſocieties and duties of relation are very much altered, which in the proper and beſt friendſhips can never be at all. But then this alſo is true: that the ſocial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Parents and Children not having in them all the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities of a proper friendſhip, cannot challenge all the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of it: that is, it is no
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110472:37"/>prejudice to the duty I owe there, to pay all the dearneſſes which are due here, and to friends there are ſome things due which the other cannot challenge: I meane, <hi>my ſecret,</hi> and <hi>my equal converſation,</hi> and the pleaſures and intereſts of theſe, and the conſequents of all.</p>
            <p>Next to this is the ſociety and dearneſſe of Brothers and Siſters: which uſually is very great amongſt worthy perſons; but if it be conſidered what it is in it ſelf, it is but very little; there is very often a likeneſſe of naturall temper, and there is a ſocial life under the ſame roof, and they are commanded to love one another, and they are equals in many inſtances, and are endeared by conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110472:38"/>when it is merry and pleaſant, innocent and ſimple, without art and without deſign. But Brothers paſſe not into noble friendſhips upon the ſtock of that relation: they have fair diſpoſitions and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, and are more eaſie and ready to ferment into the greateſt dearneſſes, if all things elſe be anſwerable. Nature diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes them well towards it, but in this inquiry if we aske what duty is paſſed upon a Brother to a Brother even for being ſo? I anſwer, that religion and our parents and God and the lawes appoint what meaſures they pleaſe; but nature paſſes but very little, and friendſhip leſſe; and this we ſee apparently in thoſe Brothers who live aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and contract new relations,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110472:38"/>and dwell in other ſocieties: There is no love, no friendſhip without the entercourſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: Friendſhips indeed may laſt longer then our abode together, but they were firſt contracted by it, and eſtabliſhed by pleaſure and benefit, and unleſſe it be the beſt kind of friendſhip (which that of Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in that meer capacity is not) it dies when it wants the proper nutriment and ſupport: and to this purpoſe is that which was ſpoken by Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: <hi>[better is a neighbour that is near, <note place="margin">Prov. 27.10.</note> then a Brother that is far off:]</hi> that is, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ordinarily, Brothers are firſt poſſeſſed of the entries and fancies of friendſhip, becauſe they are of the firſt ſocieties and converſations, yet when
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110472:39"/>that ceaſes and the Brother goes away, ſo that he does no advantage, no benefit of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; the neighbour that dwells by me, with whom if I converſe at all, either he is my enemy and does, and receives evill; or if we converſe in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſes and benefit and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant communication, he is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the lawes and meaſures of friendſhip then my diſtant Brother. And it is obſervable that <hi>[Brother]</hi> is indeed a word of friendſhip and charity and of mutual endearment, and ſo is a title of the braveſt ſociety; yet in all the Scripture there are no precepts given of any duty and comport which Brothers, that is, the deſcendents of the ſame parents are to have one towards another in that capacity, and it
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:110472:39"/>is not becauſe their nearneſſe is ſuch that they need none: For parents &amp; children are neerer, and yet need tables of duty to be deſcribed; and for Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, certainly they need it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely if there be any peculiar duty; <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> are the great probation of that, and you know who ſaid,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fratrum quoque gratia rara eſt:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It is not often you ſhall ſee</l>
                     <l>Two Brothers live in amity.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> But the Scripture which often deſcribes the duty of Parents and Children, never deſcribes the duty of Brothers; except where by <hi>Brethren</hi> are meant all that part of mankind who are tied to us by any vicinity
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110472:40"/>and indearment of religion or country, of profeſſion and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, of contract or ſociety, of love and the nobleſt friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips; the meaning is, that though fraternity alone be the endearment of ſome degrees of friendſhip, without choice and without excellency; yet the relation it ſelf is not friendſhip, and does not naturally infer it, and that which is procured by it, is but limited and little; and though it may paſſe into it, as other converſations may, yet the friendſhip is accidental to it; and enters upon other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, as it does between ſtrangers; with this onely dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference that Brotherhood does oftentimes aſſiſt the valuation of thoſe excellencies for which we entertain our friendſhips.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:110472:40"/>Fraternity is the opportunity and the preliminary diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to friendſhip, and no more. For if my Brother be a fool or a vitious perſon, the love to which nature and our firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation diſpoſes me, does not end in friendſhip, but in pity and fair proviſions, and aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; which is a demonſtration that Brotherhood is but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and addreſſe to friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and though I will love a worthy Brother more then a worthy ſtranger; if the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe be equal, becauſe the relation is ſomething, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put into the ſcales againſt an equal worthineſs muſt needs turn the ballance, as every grain will do in an even weight; yet when the relation is all the worthineſſe that is pretended,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:110472:41"/>it cannot ſtand in competition with a friend: for though a <hi>friend-Brother</hi> is better then a <hi>friend-ſtranger,</hi> where the friend is equal, but the Brother is not: yet a Brother is not better then a friend; but as <hi>Solomons</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is [there is a friend that is better then a Brother,] and to be born of the ſame pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents is ſo accidental and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick to a mans pleaſure or worthineſſe, or ſpiritual advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, that though it be very pleaſing and uſefull that a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould be a friend, yet it is no great addition to a friend that he alſo is a Brother: there is ſomething in it, but not much. But in ſhort, the caſe is thus. The firſt beginnings of friendſhip ſerve the neceſſities; but choice and worthineſſe are
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110472:41"/>the excellencies of its endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and its bravery; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Brother that is no friend, and a friend that is no Brother, there is the ſame dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference as between the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and the act or habit: a Brother if he be worthy is the readieſt and the neareſt to be a friend, but till he be ſo, he is but the twi-light of the day, and but the bloſſome to the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt fruit of Paradiſe. A Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does not alwayes make a friend, but a friend ever makes a Brother and more: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though nature ſometimes finds the tree, yet friendſhip engraves the Image; the firſt relation places him in the garden, but friendſhip ſets it in the Temple, and then only it is venerable and ſacred: and ſo is Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:110472:42"/>when it hath the ſoul of friendſhip.</p>
            <p>So that if it be asked which are moſt to be valued, Brothers or friends; the anſwer is very eaſie; Brotherhood is or may be one of the kinds of friendſhip, and from thence onely hath its value, and therefore if it be compared with a greater friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip muſt give place: But then it is not to be asked which is to be preferred, a <hi>Brother</hi> or a <hi>Friend,</hi> but which is the better friend; <hi>Memnon</hi> or my <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> For if my Brother ſayes I ought to love him beſt, then he ought to love me beſt; <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ut praeſtem Pyladen, aliquis mihi praeſtet O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſten</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hoc non fit verbis, Marce ut ameris, ama.</hi> Mar. l. 6. ep. 11.</p>
               </note> if he does, then there is a great friendſhip, and he poſſibly is to be preferred; if
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:110472:42"/>he can be that friend which he pretends to be, that is, if he be equally worthy: but if he ſayes, I muſt love him onely becauſe he is my Brother, whether he loves me or no, he is ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; and it will be a ſtrange relation which hath no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent: but ſuppoſe it, and adde this alſo, that I am equally his Brother as he is mine, &amp; then he alſo muſt love me whether I love him or no; and if he does not, he ſayes, I muſt love him though he be my Enemy; and ſo I muſt; but I muſt not love my Enemy though he be my Brother more then I love my Friend; and at laſt if he does love me for being his Brother, I confeſſe that this love de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves love again; but then I conſider, that he loves me upon
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:110472:43"/>an incompetent reaſon: for he that loves me only becauſe I am his Brother, loves me for that which is no worthineſſe, and I muſt love him as much as that comes to, and for as little reaſon; unleſſe this be added, that he loves me firſt: but whether choice and union of ſouls, and worthineſſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and greatneſſe of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and uſefulneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and the benefits of Counſel, and all thoſe endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which make our lives pleaſant and our perſons Dear, are not better and greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of love and Dearneſſe then to be born of the ſame fleſh, I think amongſt wiſe perſons needs no great enquity. For fraternity is but a Cognation of bodies, but friendſhip is an
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:110472:43"/>Union of ſouls which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federated by more noble liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. My Brother, if he be no more, ſhall have my hand to help him, but unleſſe he be my friend too, he cannot challenge my heart: and if his being my friend be the greater nearneſſe, then <hi>friend</hi> is more then <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and I ſuppoſe no man doubts but that <hi>David</hi> lov'd <hi>Jonathan</hi> far more then he lov'd his Brother <hi>Eliab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One inquity more there may be in this affair, and that is, whether a friend may be more then Husband or Wife; To which I anſwer, that it can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be reaſonable or juſt, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or lawfull: but the reaſon is, becauſe Marriage is the Queen of friendſhips, in which there is a communication of all
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:110472:44"/>that can be communicated by friendſhip: and it being made ſacred by vowes and love, by bodies and ſouls, by intereſt and cuſtome, by religion and by lawes, by common counſels, and common fortunes; it is the principal in the kind of friendſhip, and the meaſure of all the reſt: And there is no abatement to this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but that there may be ſome allay in this as in other leſſer friendſhips by the incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the perſons: if I have not choſen my friend wiſely or fortunately, he cannot be the correlative in the beſt Union; but then the friend lives as the ſoul does after death, it is in the ſtate of ſeparation, in which the ſoul ſtrangely loves the body and longs to be reunited, but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:110472:44"/>the body is an uſeleſſe trunk and can do no miniſteries to the ſoul; which therefore prayes to have the body reformed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and made a brave and a fit companion: ſo muſt theſe beſt friends, when one is uſeleſs or unapt to the braveries of the princely friendſhip, they muſt love ever, and pray ever, and long till the other be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and made fit; in this caſe there wants onely the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but the ſoul is ſtill a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and muſt be ſo for ever.</p>
            <p>A Husband and a Wife are the beſt friends, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alwayes ſignifie all that to each other which their friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips would; as the Sunne ſhines not upon a Valley which ſends up a thick vapour to cover his face; and though
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110472:45"/>his beams are eternall, yet the emiſſion is intercepted by the intervening cloud. But howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all friendſhips are but parts of this; a man muſt leave Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother and cleave to his Wife, that is <hi>[the deareſt thing in Nature is not compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the deareſt thing of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:</hi> and I think this is argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſufficient to prove friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be the greateſt band in the world; Adde to this, that other friendſhips are parts of this, they are marriages too, leſſe indeed then the other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot, muſt not be all that endearment which the other is; yet that being the principal, is the meaſure of the reſt, and are all to be honoured by like dignities, and meaſured by the ſame rules, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:110472:45"/>by their portion of the ſame Lawes: But as friendſhips are <hi>Marriages</hi> of the ſoul, and of fortunes and intereſts, and counſels; ſo they are <hi>brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods</hi> too; and I often think of the excellencies of friendſhips in the words of <hi>David,</hi> who certainly was the beſt friend in the world <hi>[Ecce quam bonum &amp; quam jucundum fratres habitare in unum:]</hi> It is good and it is pleaſant that Brethren ſhould live like friends, that is, they who are any wayes relative, and who are any wayes ſocial and confederate ſhould alſo dwell in Unity and loving ſociety, for that is the meaning of the word [Brother] in Scripture [It was my Brother <hi>Jonathan</hi>] ſaid <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> ſuch Brothers contracting ſuch friendſhips are the beauties
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:110472:46"/>of ſociety, and the pleaſure of life, and the feſtivity of minds: and whatſoever can be ſpoken of love, which is Gods eldeſt daughter, can be ſaid of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous friendſhips; and though <hi>Carneades</hi> made an eloquent oration at <hi>Rome</hi> againſt juſtice, yet never ſaw a Panegyrick of malice, or ever read that any man was witty againſt friendſhip. Indeed it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that ſome men, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves by the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarities of friendſhip excluded from the participation of thoſe beauties of ſociety which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amel and adorne the wiſe and the vertuous, might ſuppoſe themſelves to have reaſon to ſpeak the evil words of envy and detraction; I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not for all thoſe unhappy
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110472:46"/>ſoules which ſhall find heaven gates ſhut againſt them, will think they have reaſon to murmur and blaſpheme: The ſimilitude is apt enough, for that is the region of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and love is the light of that glorious Countrey, but ſo bright that it needs no Sun: Here we have fine and bright rayes of that Celeſtial flame, and though to all mankind the light of it is in ſome meaſure to be extended, like the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of light dwelling in the South, yet a little do illuſtrate and beautifie the North, yet ſome live under the line, and the beams of friendſhip in that poſition are imminent and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular.</p>
            <p>I know but one thing more in which the Communications
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:110472:47"/>of friendſhip can be reſtrained; and that is, in Friends and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: <hi>Amicus amici, amicus meus non eſt:</hi> My friends friend is not alwayes my friend; nor his enemy mine; for if my friend quarrel with a third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with whom he hath had no friendſhips, upon the account of intereſt; if that third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be my friend, the nobleneſs of our friendſhips deſpiſes ſuch a quarrel; and what may be reaſonable in him, would be ignoble in me; ſometimes it may be otherwiſe, and friends may marry one anothers loves and hatreds, but it is by chance if it can be juſt, and therefore <hi>becauſe it is not alwayes right it cannot be ever neceſſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all things elſe, let friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips be as high and expreſſive
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:110472:47"/>till they become an Union, or that friends like the Molionidae be ſo the ſame that the flames of their dead bodies make but one Piramis; no charity can be reproved, and ſuch friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips which are more then ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, are nothing elſe but the rayes of that glorious grace drawn into one centre, and made more active by the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and the proper ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are well repreſented in the old Hieroglyphick, by which the ancients depicted friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:
<q>In the beauties and ſtrength of a young man, bare-headed, rudely clothed, to ſignifie its activity, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingneſs, readineſs of action, and aptneſſes to do ſervice; Upon the fringes of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was written <hi>Mors &amp;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:110472:48"/>vita,</hi> as ſignifying that <hi>in life and death</hi> the friendſhip was the ſame; on the forehead was written <hi>Summer and Winter,</hi> that is, proſperous and adverſe accidents and ſtates of life; the left arme and ſhoulder was bare and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked downe to the heart to which the finger pointed, and there was written <hi>longè &amp; propè:</hi>
               </q> by all which we know that friendſhip does good far and neer: in Summer &amp; Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in life and death, and knows no difference of ſtate or acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent but by the variety of her ſervices: and therefore ask no more to what we can be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by friendſhip; for it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that can be <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>prudent, uſefull</hi> and <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:110472:48"/>
            <p>For this is all the allay of this Univerſality, we may do any thing or ſuffer any thing, that is <hi>wiſe</hi> or <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or <hi>greatly beneficial</hi> to my friend, and that <hi>in any thing,</hi> in which I am <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect maſter</hi> of my <hi>perſon</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</hi> But I would not in bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very viſite my friend when he is ſick of the plague, unleſſe I can do him good equall at leaſt to my danger, but I will procure him Phyſicians and prayers, all the aſſiſtances that he can receive, and that he can deſire, if they be in my power: and when he is dead, I will not run into his grave and be ſtifled with his earth; but I will mourn for him, and performe his will, and take care of his relatives, and do for him as if he were alive, and I think that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:110472:49"/>is the meaning of that hard ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Greek Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>To me though diſtant let thy friendſhip flye,</l>
                  <l>Though men be mortal, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips muſt not die.</l>
                  <l>Of all things elſe there's great ſatiety.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Of ſuch immortal abſtracted pure friendſhips indeed there is no great plenty, and to ſee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hate each other, is not ſo rare as to ſee them love at this rate. <hi>The dead and the abſent have but few friends,</hi> ſay the Spaniards; but they who are the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:110472:49"/>ſame to their friend <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when he is in another Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, or in another World, theſe are they who are fit to preſerve the ſacred fire for eternall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and to perpetuate the memory of thoſe exemplar friendſhips of the beſt men which have filled the world with hiſtory and wonder: for in no other ſenſe but this, can it be true; that friendſhips are pure loves, regarding to doe good more then to receive it: He that is a friend after death, hopes not for a recompenſe from his friend, and makes no bargain either for fame or love; but is rewarded with the conſcience and ſatisfaction of doing bravely: but then this is demonſtration that they chooſe Friends beſt who take
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:110472:50"/>perſons ſo worthy that can and will do ſo: This is the profit and uſefulneſſe of friendſhip; and he that contracts ſuch a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Union, muſt take care that his friend be ſuch who can and will; but hopes that himſelfe ſhall be firſt uſed, and put to act it: I will not have ſuch a friendſhip that is good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but I hope that I ſhall be on the giving and aſſiſting part; and yet if both the friends be ſo noble and hope and ſtrive to do the benefit, I cannot well ſay which ought to yield, and whether that friendſhip were braver that could be content to be unproſperous ſo his friend might have the glory of aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him; or that which deſires to give aſſiſtances in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt meaſures of friendſhip:
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:110472:50"/>but he that chooſes a worthy friend that himſelf in the dayes of ſorrow and need might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the advantage, hath no excuſe, no pardon, unleſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be as certain to do aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces when evil fortune ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them. The ſumme of this anſwer to this enquiry I give you in a pair of Greek ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Friends are to friends as leſſer Gods, while they</l>
                  <l>Honour and ſervice to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pay.</l>
                  <l>But when a dark cloud comes, grudge not to lend</l>
                  <l>Thy head, thy heart, thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to thy friend.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:110472:51"/>
            <p n="3">3. The laſt inquiry is, <hi>how friendſhips are to be conducted?</hi> That is, what are <hi>the duties in preſence and in abſence; whether the friend may not deſire to enjoy his friend as well as his friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi> The anſwer to which in a great meaſure depends upon what I have ſaid already: &amp; if friendſhip be a charity in ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and is not for contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and noiſe, but for materiall comforts and noble treatments and uſages, this is no peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but that if I buy land, I may eat the fruits, and if I take a houſe I may dwell in it; and if I love a worthy perſon, I may pleaſe my ſelf in his ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and in this there is no excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unleſſe the friendſhip be between perſons of a different ſex: for then not onely the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:110472:51"/>of their religion, and the care of their honour, but the worthineſs of their friendſhip requires that their entercourſe be prudent and free from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion and reproch: and if a friend is obliged to bear a cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, ſo he ſecure the honour of his friend, it will concerne him to conduct his entercouſe in the lines of a vertuous pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſo that he ſhall rather loſe much of <hi>his own comfort,</hi> then ſhe any thing of <hi>her honour;</hi> and in this caſe the noiſes of people are ſo to be regarded, that next to innocence they are the principall. But when by caution and prudence and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere conduct, a friend hath done all that he or ſhe can to ſecure fame and honourable reports; after this, their noiſes are to be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:110472:52"/>deſpiſed; they muſt not fright us from our friendſhips, nor from her faireſt entercourſes; <hi>I may lawfully pluck the cluſters from my own vine, though he that walks by, calls me thief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by the way (Madam) you may ſee how much I differ from the moroſity of thoſe Cynics who would not admit your ſex into the communities of a noble friendſhip. I believe ſome Wives have been the beſt friends in the world; and few ſtories can out-do the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe and piety of that Lady that ſuck'd the poyſonous, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent matter from the wound of our brave Prince in the holy Land, when an Aſſaſine had pierc'd him with a venom'd ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; and if it be told that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cannot retain counſell,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:110472:52"/>and therefore can be no brave friends; I can beſt confute them by the ſtory of <hi>Porcia,</hi> who being fearfull of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her ſex, ſtabb'd her ſelf into the thigh to try how ſhe could bear pain; and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her ſelf conſtant enough to that ſufferance, gently chid her <hi>Brutus</hi> for not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to truſt her, ſince now ſhe perceived that no torment could wreſt that ſecret from her, which ſhe hoped might be intruſted to her. If there were not more things to be ſaid for your ſatisfaction, I could have made it diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble whether have been more illuſtrious in their friendſhips men or women? I cannot ſay that Women are capable of all thoſe excellencies by which
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:110472:53"/>men can oblige the world; and therefore a female friend in ſome caſes is not ſo good a counſellor as a wiſe man, and cannot ſo well defend my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; nor diſpoſe of reliefs and aſſiſtances if ſhe be under the power of another: but a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can love as paſſionately, and converſe as pleaſantly, and retain a ſecret as faithfully, and be uſefull in her proper mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; and ſhe can die for her friend as well as the braveſt Roman Knight, and we finde that ſome perſons have engag'd themſelves as far as death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a leſs intereſt then all this amounts to: ſuch were the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Greeks call them, the Devoti of a Prince or General, the Aſſaſines amongſt the <hi>Saracens,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:110472:53"/>the old <hi>Galatians:</hi> they did as much as a friend could do; and if the greateſt ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a friend can be paid for by an ignoble price, we cannot grudge to vertuous and brave women that they be partners in a noble friendſhip, ſince their converſation and returns can adde ſo many moments to the felicity of our lives: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though a Knife cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as farre as a Sword, yet a Knife may be more uſefull to ſome purpoſes; and in every thing, except it be againſt an enemy. A man is the beſt friend in trouble, but a woman may be equall to him in the dayes of joy: a woman can as well increaſe our comforts, but cannot ſo well leſſen our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows: and therefore we do not carry
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:110472:54"/>women with us when we go to fight; but in peaceful Cities and times, vertuous women are the beauties of ſociety and the prettineſſes of friendſhip. And when we conſider that few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the world have all thoſe excellencies by which friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip can be uſeful and illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, we may as well allow wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as men to be friends; ſince <hi>they</hi> can have all that which can be neceſſary and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to friendſhips, and <hi>theſe</hi> cannot have all by which friendſhips can be accidentally improved; in all ſome abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will be made; &amp; we ſhall do too much honour to women if we reject them from friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips becauſe they are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: for if to friendſhips we admit imperfect men, becauſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:110472:54"/>no man is perfect: he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects women does find fault with them becauſe they are not more perfect then men, which either does ſecretly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that they ought and can be perfect, or elſe it openly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes men of injuſtice and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality.</p>
            <p>I hope you will pardon me that I am a little gone from my undertaking, I went aſide to wait upon the women and to do countenance to their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vertues: I am now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, and, if I were to doe the office of a guide to unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed friends, would adde the particulars following: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, you need not read them now, but when any friends come to be taught by your precept and example how to converſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:110472:55"/>in the nobleſt conjurations, you may put theſe into better words and tell them</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the firſt law of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is, they muſt neither ask of their friend what is Undecent; nor grant it if themſelves be askt. For it is no good office to make my friend more viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or more a fool; I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain his folly, but not nurſe it; I will not make my groom the officer of my luſt and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. There are Villains who ſell their ſouls for bread, that offer ſin and vanity at a price: I ſhould be unwilling my friend ſhould know I am vitious; but if he could be brought to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to it; he is not worthy to be my friend: and if I could of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to him, I do not deſerve to claſp hands with a vertuous perſon.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:110472:55"/>
            <p n="2">2. Let no man chooſe him for his friend whom it ſhall be poſſible for him ever after to hate, for though the <hi>ſociety</hi> may juſtly be interrupted, yet <hi>love</hi> is an immortal thing, and I will never deſpiſe him whom I could once think worthy of my love. A friend that proves not good is rather to be ſuffered, then any enmities be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: and there are ſome outer offices of friendſhip and little drudgeries in which the leſs worthy are to be imployed, and it is better that he be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſtairs then quite thrown out of doors.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There are two things which a friend can never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, a treacherous blow and the revealing of a ſecret, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe are againſt the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:110472:56"/>of friendſhip; they are the adulteries of it, and diſſolve the Union; and in the matters of friendſhip which is the marriage of ſouls; theſe are the proper cauſes of divorce: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall adde this only, that <hi>ſecrecy</hi> is the <hi>chaſtity of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and the publication of it is a proſtitution and direct debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery; but a ſecret, treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous wound is a perfect and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable Apoſtacy. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a pretty apologue that <hi>Bromiard</hi> tells, A Fowler in a ſharp froſty morning having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken many little birds for which he had long watched, began to take up his nets; and nipping the birds on the head laid them down. A young thruſh eſpying the tears trickling down his cheeks by the reaſon of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:110472:56"/>cold, ſaid to her Mother, that certainly the man was very mercifull and compaſſionate that wept ſo bitterly over the calamity of the poor Birds. But her Mother told her more wiſely, that ſhe might better judge of the mans diſpoſition by his hand then by his eye; and if the hands do ſtrike trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly, he can never be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to friendſhip, who ſpeaks fairly and weeps pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. Friendſhip is the greateſt honeſty and ingenuity in the world.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Never accuſe thy friend, nor believe him that does; if thou doſt, thou haſt broken the skin; but he that is angry with every little fault breaks the bones of friendſhip; and when we conſider that in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:110472:57"/>and the accidents of every day, in which no man is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly pleaſed or diſpleaſed with the ſame things; we ſhall find reaſon to impute the change unto our ſelves; and the emanations of the Sun are ſtill glorious, when our eyes are ſore: and we have no reaſon to be angry with an eternall light, becauſe we have a changeable and a mortall faculty. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, do not think thou didſt contract alliance with an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, when thou didſt take thy friend into thy boſome; he may be weak as well as thou art, and thou mayeſt need pardon as well as he, and
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:110472:57"/>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. </l>
                  <bibl>Theog.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>that man loves flattery more then friendſhip, who would not onely have his friend, but all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies of his friend to humour him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Give thy friend counſel wiſely and charitably, but leave him to his liberty whether he will follow thee or no: and be not angry if thy counſel be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected: for, <hi>advice is no Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> and he is not my friend that will be my Judge whether I will or no. <hi>Neoptolemus</hi> had never been honoured with the victory and ſpoiles of <hi>Troy</hi> if he had attended to the tears and counſel of <hi>Lycomedes,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afraid to venture the young
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:110472:58"/>man, faine would have had him ſleep at home ſafe in his little Iſland. He that gives advice to his friend and <hi>exacts obedience</hi> to it, does not the kindneſſe and ingenuity of a friend, but the office and pertneſſe of a Schoolmaſter.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Never be a Judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thy friends in any matter where both ſet their hearts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the victory: If ſtrangers or enemies be litigants, what ever ſide thou favoureſt, thou get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt a friend, but when friends are the parties thou loſeſt one.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Never comport thy ſelf ſo, as that thy friend can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of thee: for then the ſtate of the relation alters when a new and troubleſome paſſion ſupervenes. <hi>ODERUNT quos METUUNT. Perfect love
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:110472:58"/>caſteth out feare,</hi> and no man is friend to a Tyrant; but that friendſhip is Tyranny where the love is changed into fear, equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity into empire, ſociety into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; for then all my kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him alſo will he no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then flattery.</p>
            <p n="8">8. When you admoniſh your friend, let it be without bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe; when you chide him, let it be without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch; when you praiſe him, let it be with worthy pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and for juſt cauſes, and in friendly meaſures; too much of that is flattery, too little is envy; if you doe it juſtly you teach him true meaſures: but when others praiſe him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, though they praiſe not thee, and remember that if thou eſteemeſt his praiſe to be thy
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:110472:59"/>diſparagement, thou art envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but neither juſt nor kind.</p>
            <p n="9">9. When all things elſe are equal preferre an old friend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a new. If thou meaneſt to ſpend thy friend, and make a gain of him till he be weary, thou wilt eſteeme him as a beaſt of burden, the worſe for his age; But if thou eſteemeſt him by noble meaſures, he will be better to thee by thy being uſed to him, by triall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, by reciprocation of indearments, and an habituall worthineſs. An old friend is like old wine, which when a man hath drunk, he doth not deſire new, becauſe he ſaith the old is better. But every old friend was new once; and if he be worthy keep the new one till he become old.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:110472:59"/>
            <p n="10">10. After all this, treat thy friend nobly, love to be with him, do to him all the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of love and fair endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to thy capacity and his; Bear with his infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties till they approch towards being criminal; but never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble with him, never deſpiſe him, never leave him. <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <q>
                     <l>Extra fortunam eſt quicquid donatur amicis;</l>
                     <l>Quas dederis ſolas ſemper habebis opes.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mart. l. 5. ep. 43.</hi>
                     </bibl> 
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Et tamen hoc vitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed non leve, ſit licet unu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
                     <l>Quod colit ingratas pauper amicitias.</l>
                     <l>Quis largitur opes veteri fido<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſodali?</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ep. 19.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </note> Give him gifts and upbraid him not,
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <q>
                     <l>Non bellè quaedam faciunt duo: ſufficit unus</l>
                     <l>Huic operi: ſi vis ut loquar ipſe tace.</l>
                     <l>Crede mihi quamvis ingentia Poſtume dones,</l>
                     <l>Authoris pereunt garrulitate ſui.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ep. 53.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </note> and refuſe not his kindneſſes, and be ſure never to deſpiſe the ſmallneſs or the impropriety of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:110472:60"/>them. <hi>Confirmatur amor beneficio accepto:</hi> A gift (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) faſteneth friendſhips; for as an eye that dwels long upon a ſtar muſt de refreſhed with leſſer beauties and ſtrengthened with greens and looking-glaſſes, leſt the ſight become amazed with too great a ſplendor; ſo muſt the love of friends ſometimes be refreſhed with material and low Careſſes; leſt by ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to <hi>be too divine</hi> it becomes <hi>leſs humane:</hi> It muſt be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed its ſhare of <hi>both:</hi> It is <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> in giving pardon and fair conſtruction, and openneſs and ingenuity, and keeping ſecrets; it hath <hi>ſomething</hi> that is <hi>divine,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>beneficent;</hi> but <hi>much</hi> becauſe it is <hi>eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <div type="half_title">
               <pb facs="tcp:110472:60"/>
               <p>TWO LETTERS TO PERSONS Changed in their RELIGION.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:110472:61"/>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:110472:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Copy of the Firſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter written to a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman newly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the Church of</hi> Rome.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>M. B.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was deſirous of an opportunity in <hi>London</hi> to have diſcourſed with you concerning ſomething of neareſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to you, but the multitude of my little affairs hindred me, and have brought upon you this trouble to read a long Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which yet I hope you will
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:110472:62"/>be more willing to do, becauſe it comes from one who hath a great reſpect to your perſon, and a very great charity to your ſoul: I muſt confeſſe I was on your behalf troubled when I heard you were fallen from the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and entred into a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, unneceſſary ſchiſm, and departure from the Lawes of the King, and the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thoſe with whom you have alwayes lived in charity, going againſt thoſe Lawes in the defence and profeſſion of which your Husband died, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Religion in which you were Baptized, in which for ſo many years, you lived piouſly and hoped for Heaven, and all this without any ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent reaſon, without neceſſity
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:110472:62"/>or juſt ſcandall miniſtred to you; and to aggravate all this, you did it in a time when the Church of <hi>England</hi> was perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, when ſhe was marked with the Characteriſmes of her Lord, the marks of the Croſſe of Jeſus, that is, when ſhe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for a holy cauſe and a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſcience, when the Church of <hi>England</hi> was more glorious then at any time before,; Even when ſhe could ſhew more Martyrs and Confeſſors then any Church this day in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, even then when a King died in the profeſſion of her Religion, and thouſands of Prieſts, learned and pious men ſuffered the ſpoiling of their goods rather then they would forſake one Article of ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Religion; So that ſeriouſly
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:110472:63"/>it is not eaſily to be imagined that any thing ſhould move you, unleſſe it be that which troubled the perverſe Jewes, and the Heathen Greek, <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulum crucis,</hi> the ſcandall of the Croſſe; You ſtumbled at that Rock of offence, You left us becauſe we were afflicted, leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in outward circumſtances and wrapped in a cloud; but give me leave only to reminde you of that ſad ſaying of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that you may avoid the conſequent of it; <hi>They that fall on this ſtone ſhall be broken in pieces, but they on whom it ſhall fall ſhall be grinded to powder.</hi> And if we ſhould conſider things but prudently, it is a great argument that the ſons of our Church are very conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and juſt in their perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:110472:63"/>when it is evident, that we have no temporall end to ſerve, nothing but the great end of our ſouls, all our hopes of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment are gone, all ſecular regards, only we ſtill have truth on our ſides, and we are not willing with the loſſe of truth to change from a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a proſperous Church, from a Reformed to a Church that will not be reformed; leſt we give ſcandall to good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that ſuffer for a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and weaken the hands of the afflicted; of which if you had been more carefull you would have remained much more innocent.</p>
               <p>But I pray, give me leave to conſider for you, becauſe you in your change conſidered ſo little for your ſelf, what fault,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:110472:64"/>what falſe doctrine, what wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or dangerous propoſition, what defect, what amiſſe did you find in the Doctrine and Liturgy and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For its doctrine,</hi> It is certain it profeſſes the belief of all that is written in the Old and New Teſtament, all that which is in the three Creeds, the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical, the Nicene, and that of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and whatſoever was decreed in the four General Councels, or in any other truly ſuch, and whatſoever was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in theſe, our Church hath legally declared it to be Hereſie. And upon theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts above four whole ages of the Church went to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; they baptized all their Catechumens into this faith,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:110472:64"/>their hopes of heaven was upon this and a good life, their Saints and Martyrs lived and died in this alone, they denied Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to none that profeſſed this faith. This is the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick faith, ſo ſaith the Creed of <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> and unleſſe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men have power to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the faith of God, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver live and die in this faith, are intirely <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> So that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath the ſame faith without dlſpute that the Church had for 400 or 500 years, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there could be nothing wanting here to ſaving faith, if we live according to our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>For the Liturgy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I ſhall not need to ſay much, becauſe the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:110472:65"/>caſe will be very evident; Firſt, Becauſe the diſputers of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have not been very forward to object any thing againſt it, they cannot charge it with any evil: 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for all the time of K. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6 and till the eleventh year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> your people came to our Churches and prayed with us till the Bull of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> came out upon temporal regards, and made a Schiſm by forbidding the Queens Subjects to pray as by Law was here appointed, though the prayers were good and holy, as themſelves did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. That Bull enjoyned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſancy, and made that which was as an act of Rebellion, and Diſobedience, &amp; Schiſme, to be the character of your Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:110472:65"/>Catholikes. And after this, what can be ſuppoſed wanting in order to ſalvation? We have the Word of God, the Faith of the Apoſtles, the Creeds of the Primitive Church, the Articles of the four firſt generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, a holy Liturgy, excellent Prayers, perfect Sacraments, Faith and Repentance, the ten Commandements, and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of Chriſt, and all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and counſels of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; We teach the neceſſity of good works, and require and ſtrictly exact the ſeverity of a holy life; We live in obedience to God, and are ready to die for him, and doe ſo when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires us ſo to doe; We ſpeak honour of his moſt holy Name, we worſhip him at the mention of his Name, we confeſſe his
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:110472:66"/>Attributes, we love his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, we pray for all men, we love all Chriſtians, even our moſt erring Brethren, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſinnes to God and to our Brethren whom we have offended, and to Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in caſes of Scandall, or of a troubled Conſcience, We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnicate often, we are enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to receive the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thrice every year at leaſt; Our Prieſts abſolve the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, our Biſhops ordain Prieſts, and confirm baptized perſons, and bleſſe their people and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede for them; and what could here be wanting to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? what neceſſity forced you from us? I dare not ſuſpect it was a temporal regard that drew you away, but I am ſure it could be no ſpirituall.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:110472:66"/>
               <p>But now that I have told you, and made you to conſider from whence you went, give me leave to repreſent to you, and tell you whither you are gone, that you may underſtand the nature and conditions of your change: For doe not think your ſelf ſafe, becauſe they tell you that you are come to the Church; You are indeed gone from one Church to another, from a better to a worſe, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the induction, the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of which before I reckon, give me leave to give you this advice; if you mean in this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair to underſtand what you do; it were better you enquired what your Religion is, then what your Church is; for that which is a true Religion to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:110472:67"/>day, will be ſo to morrow and for ever; but that which is a holy Church to day, may be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical at the next change, or may betray her truſt, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude new Articles in contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the old, or by new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations may elude anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent truths, or may change your Creed, or may pretend to be the Spouſe of Chriſt when ſhe is idolatrous, that is, adulterous to God: Your Religion is that which you muſt, and therefore may competently underſtand; You muſt live in it, and grow in it, and govern all the actions of your life by it; and in all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions concerning the Church, you are to chooſe your Church by the Religion, and therefore this ought firſt and laſt to be enquired after. Whether the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:110472:67"/>Romane Church be the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, muſt depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo many uncertain enquiries, is offered to be proved by ſo long, ſo tedious a method, hath in it ſo many intrigues and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinths of Queſtion, and is (like a long line) ſo impoſſible to be perfectly ſtrait, and to have no declination in it when it is held by ſuch a hand as yours, that unleſſe it be by material enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries into the Articles of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, you can never hope to have juſt grounds of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. In the mean time you can conſider this; if the Roman Church were the Catholike, that is, ſo as to exclude all that are not of her communion, then the Greek Churches had as good turn Turks as remain damned Chriſtians, and all that
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:110472:68"/>are in the communion of all the other Patriarchal Churches in Chriſtendome, muſt alſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh like Heathens, which thing before any man can beleeve, he muſt have put off all reaſon, and all modeſty, and all charity; And who can with any probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity think that <hi>the Communion of Saints</hi> in the Creed is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the <hi>Communion of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Subjects,</hi> and the Article of the Catholike Church was made up to diſpark the inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but to turn them into the pale of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Church is as limited as ever it was, ſave onely that the Synagogue is tranſlated to <hi>Rome,</hi> which I think you will eaſily beleeve was a Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Apoſtles underſtood not. But though it be hard
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:110472:68"/>to truſt to it, it is alſo ſo hard to prove it, that you ſhall never be able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meaſures of that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and therefore your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation can never depend upon it. For no good or wiſe perſon can beleeve that God hath ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Salvation to impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meaſures, or bound us to an Article that is not by us cognoſcible, or intends to have us conducted by that which we cannot underſtand, and when you ſhall know that Learned men, even of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane party are not agreed concerning the Catholique Church that is infallibly to guide you, ſome ſaying that it is the virtual Church, that is, the Pope; ſome, that it is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative Church, that is, a
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:110472:69"/>Councel; Some, that it is the Pope and the Councel, the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Church and the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Church together; Some, that neither of theſe, nor both together are infallible; but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the eſſentiall Church, or the diffuſive Church is the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, from whom we muſt at no hand diſſent; you will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find your ſelf in a wood, and uncertain whether you have more then a word in exchange for your ſoul, when you are told you are in the Catholique Church. But I will tell you what you may underſtand, and ſee, and feel, ſomething that your ſelf can tell whether I ſay true or no concerning it. You are now gone to a Church that protects it ſelf by arts of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty and arms, by violence and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:110472:69"/>perſecuting all that are not of their minds, to a Church in which you are to be a Subject of the King ſo long as it pleaſes the Pope: In which you may be abſolved from your Vows made to God, your Oathes to the King, your Promiſes to Men, your duty to your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in ſome caſes: A Church in which men pray to God and to Saints in the ſame Form of words in which they pray to God, as you may ſee in the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Saints, and particularly of our Lady: a Church in which men are taught by moſt of the principal Leaders to worſhip Images with the ſame worſhip with which they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God and Chriſt, or him or her whoſe Image it is, and in which they uſually picture God
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:110472:70"/>the Father, and the holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to the great diſhonour of that ſacred myſterie, againſt the doctrine and practice of the Primitive Church, againſt the expreſſe doctrine of Scripture, againſt the honour of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Attribute; I mean, the immenſity and ſpirituality of the Divine Nature; You are gone to a Church that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be Infallible, and yet is infinitely deceived in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particulars, and yet endures no contradiction, and is impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient her children ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into any thing her Prieſts obtrude. You are gone from receiving the whole Sacrament to receive it but half; from Chriſts Inſtitution to a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane invention, from Scripture to uncertain Traditions, and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:110472:70"/>from ancient Traditions to new pretences, from prayers which ye undeſtood to prayers which ye underſtand not, from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God to rely upon creatures, from intire depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon inward acts to a dangerous temptation of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting too much in outward miniſteries, in the externall work of Sacraments and of Sacramentals: You are gone from a Church whoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping is ſimple, Chriſtian and Apoſtolical, to a Church where mens conſciences are loaden with a burden of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies greater then that in the dayes of the Jewiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (for the Ceremonial of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a great Book in Folio) greater I ſay then all the Ceremonies
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:110472:71"/>of the Jews contained in <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> &amp;c. You are gone from a Church where you were exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to read the Word of God, the holy Scriptures from whence you found inſtruction, inſtitution, comfort, reproof, a treaſure of all excellencies, to a Church that ſeals up that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from you, and gives you drink by drops out of ſuch Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns as they firſt make, and then ſtain, and then reach out: and if it be told you that ſome men abuſe Scripture, it is true, for if your Prieſts had not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Scripture, they could not thus have abuſed you, but there is no neceſſity they ſhould, and you need not, unleſſe you liſt; any more then you need to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the Sacraments or decrees of the Church, or the meſſages
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:110472:71"/>of your friend, or the Letters you receive, or the Laws of the Land, all which are liable to be abuſed by evil perſons, but not by good people and modeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings. It is now become a part of your Religion to be ignorant, to walk in blindneſſe, to believe the man that hears your Confeſſions, to hear none but him, not to hear God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king but by him, and ſo you are liable to be abuſed by him, as he pleaſe, without remedy. You are gone from us, where you were onely taught to worſhip God through Jeſus Chriſt, and now you are taught to worſhip Saints and Angels with a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at leaſt dangerous, and in ſome things proper to God; for your Church worſhips the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary</hi> with burning incenſe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:110472:72"/>and candles to her, and you give her preſents, which by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all Nations uſed to be eſteemed a worſhip peculiar to God, and it is the ſame thing which was condemned for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie in the <hi>Collyridians,</hi> who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a Cake to the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> A Candle and a Cake make no difference in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and your joyning God and the Saints in your worſhip and devotions, is like the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of them that fought for King and Parliament, the latter deſtroys the former. I will trouble you with no more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, becauſe if theſe move you not to conſider better, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can.</p>
               <p>But yet I have two things more to adde of another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, one of which at leaſt may
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:110472:72"/>prevail upon you, whom I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to have a tender and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Conſcience.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, That all the points of difference between us and your Church are ſuch as do evidently ſerve the ends of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe and ambition, of power and riches, and ſo ſtand vehemently ſuſpected of deſign, and art, rather then truth of the Article and deſigns upon Heaven. I inſtance in the Popes power over Princes and all the world; his power of diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, The exemption of the Clergy from juriſdiction of Princes, The doctrine of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory and Indulgences which was once made means to raiſe a portion for a Lady, the Neece of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth; The Prieſts power advanced beyond
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:110472:73"/>authority of any warrant from Scripture, a doctrine apt to bring abſolute obedience to the Papacy; but becauſe this is poſſibly too nice for you to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect or conſider, that which I am ſure ought to move you is this.</p>
               <p>That you are gone to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in which though through Gods grace prevailing over the follies of men, there are I hope, and charitably ſuppoſe many pious men that love God, and live good lives, yet there are very many doctrines taught by your men, which are very ill Friends to a good life. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in your Indulgences and pardons, In which vitious men put a great confidence, and rely greatly upon them. The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Purgatory which gives
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:110472:73"/>countenance to a ſort of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians who live half to God and half to the world, and for them this doctrine hath found out a way that they may go to Hell and to Heaven too. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that the Prieſts abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can turn a trifling repentance into a perfect and a good, and that ſuddenly too, and at any time, even on our death-bed, or the minute before your death, is a dangerous heap of falſhoods, and gives licence to wicked people, and teaches men to reconcile a wicked debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed life, with the hopes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And then for penances and temporal ſatisfaction, which might ſeem to be as a plank after the ſhipwrack of the duty of Repentance, to keep men in awe, and to preſerve them from
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:110472:74"/>ſinking in an Ocean of Impiety, it comes to juſt nothing by your doctrine; for there are ſo many eaſie wayes of Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and getting Pardons, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny con-fraternities, ſtations, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg'd Altars, little Offices, <hi>Agnus Dei</hi>'s, amulets, hallowed devices, ſwords, roſes, hats, Churchyards, and the fountain of theſe annexed indulgences the Pope himſelf, and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of granting what, and when, and to whom he liſt, that he is a very unfortunate man that needs to ſmart with penances; and after all, he may chooſe to ſuffer any at all, for he may pay them in Purgatory if he pleaſe, and he may come out of Purgatory upon reaſonable terms, in caſe he ſhould think it fit to go thither; So that all
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:110472:74"/>the whole duty of <hi>Repentance</hi> ſeems to be deſtroyed with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of men that ſeek power and gain, and find errour and folly; inſomuch that if I had a mind to live an evil Life, and yet hope for Heaven at laſt, I would be of your religion above any in the world.</p>
               <p>But I forget I am writing a Letter: I ſhall therefore deſire you to conſider upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, which is the ſafer way. For ſurely it is lawfull for a man to ſerve God without Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; but that to worſhip Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is lawfull, is not ſo ſure. It is lawfull to pray to God alone, to confeſſe him to be true, and every man a liar, to call no man Maſter upon Earth, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie upon God teaching us; But it is at leaſt hugely diſputable
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:110472:75"/>and not at all certain that any man, or ſociety of men can be infallible, that we may put our truſt in Saints, in certain extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Images, or burne In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe and offer conſumptive oblations to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or make vows to perſons, of whoſe ſtate, or place, or capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, or condition we have no certain revelation: we are ſure we doe well when in the holy Communion we worſhip God and Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour, but they who alſo worſhip what ſeems to be bread, are put to ſtrange ſhifts to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves believe it to be lawfull. It is certainly lawfull to believe what we ſee and feel; but it is an unnaturall thing upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of faith to disbelieve our eyes, when our ſenſe and our
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:110472:75"/>faith can better be reconciled, as it is in the queſtion of the Reall preſence, as it is taught by the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that unleſſe you mean to prefer a danger before ſafety, temptation to unholineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a ſevere and a holy religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, unleſſe you mean to loſe the benefit of your prayers by praying what you perceive not, and the benefit of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in great degrees by fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from Chriſts inſtitution, and taking half inſtead of all; unleſſe you deſire to provoke God to jealouſie by Images, and Man to jealouſie in profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a Religion in which you may in many caſes have leave to forfeit your faith and lawfull truſt, unleſſe you will ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to give ſcandall to thoſe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:110472:76"/>good people with whom you have lived in a common Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and weaken the hearts of Gods afflicted ones, unleſſe you will chooſe a Catechiſm with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſecond Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a Faith that grows bigger or leſſe as men pleaſe, and a Hope that in many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees relyes on men and vain confidences, and a Charity that damns all the world but your ſelves, unleſſe you will doe all this, that is, ſuffer an abuſe in your Prayers, in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the Commandments, in Faith, in Hope, in Charity, in the Communion of Saints, and your duty to your Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, you muſt return to the boſome of your Mother the Church of ENGLAND from whence you have fallen, rather
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:110472:76"/>weakly then maliciouſly, and I doubt not but you will find the Comfort of it all your Life, and in the Day of your Death, and in the Day of Judgment. If you will not, yet I have freed mine own ſoule, and done an act of Duty and Charity, which at leaſt you are bound to take kindly if you will not entertain it obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diently.</p>
               <p>Now let me adde this, that although moſt of theſe obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are ſuch things which are the open and avowed do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines or practices of your Church, and need not to be proved as being either notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or confeſſed; yet if any of your Guides ſhall ſeem to queſtion any thing of it, I will bind my ſelfe to verifie it to a
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:110472:77"/>tittle, and in that ſenſe too which I intend them, that is, ſo as to be an objection obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging you to return, under the pain of folly or hereſie, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, according to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter. And though I have propounded theſe things now to your conſideration, yet if it be deſired I ſhall repreſent them to your eye, ſo that even your ſelf ſhall be able to give ſentence in the behalf of truth. In the mean time give me leave to tell you of how much folly you are guilty in being moved by ſuch mock-arguments as your men uſe when they meet with women and tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences and weaker underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
               <p>The firſt is; where was your Church before <hi>Luther?</hi> Now if
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:110472:77"/>you had called upon them to ſpeak ſomething againſt your religion from Scripture, or right reaſon, or Univerſal Tradition, you had been ſecure as a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toiſe in her ſhell; a cart preſſed with ſheavs could not have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed your cauſe or perſon; though you had confeſſed you underſtood nothing of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of ſucceſſion doctrinal or perſonall. For if we can make it appeare that our religion was that which Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught, let the truth ſuffer what eclipſes or prejudices can be ſuppoſed, let it be hid like the holy fire in the captivity, yet what Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught us is eternally true, and ſhall by ſome means or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be conveyed to us; even the enemies of truth have been
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:110472:78"/>conſervators of that truth by which we can confute their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. But if you ſtill aske where it was before <hi>Luther?</hi> I anſwer it was there where it was after; even in the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament; and I know no warrant for any other religion; and if you will expect I ſhould ſhew any ſociety of men who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed all the doctrines which are now expreſſed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> I ſhall tell you it is unreaſonable; becauſe ſome of our truths are now brought into our publick confeſſions that they might be oppos'd againſt your errors; before the occaſion of which there was no need of any ſuch confeſſions, till you made many things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:110472:78"/>to be profeſſed, which are not lawfull to be believed. For if we believe your ſuperinduc'd follies we ſhall do unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, unconſcionably, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly; but the queſtions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are ſo uſeleſſe abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the accidental ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity which your follies have brought upon us, that it had been happy if we had never heard of them more then the Saints and Martyrs did in the firſt ages of the Church; but becauſe your Clergy have inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the liberty of the Church, and multiplyed the dangers of damnation, and pretend new neceſſities, and have introduc'd new articles, and affright the ſimple upon new pretenſions, and ſlight the very inſtitution and the Commands of Chriſt
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:110472:79"/>and of the Apoſtles, and invent new Sacramentals conſtituting Ceremonies of their own head, and promiſe grace along with the uſe of them, as if they were not Miniſters but Lords of the Spirit, and teach for doctrines the commandments of men, and make void the Commandment of God by their tradition, and have made a ſtrange body of Divinity, therefore it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that we ſhould immure our Faith by the refuſal of ſuch vain and ſuperſtitious dreams: but our faith was completed at firſt, it is no other then that which was delivered to the Saints, and can be no more for ever.</p>
               <p>So that it is a fooliſh demand to require that we ſhould ſhew before <hi>Luther</hi> a ſyſteme of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:110472:79"/>declaring our ſenſe in theſe queſtions: It was long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were queſtions at all; and when they were made que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, they remained ſo, a long time; and when by their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall pieces they were determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, this part of the Church was oppreſſed with a violent pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and when God gave oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, then the yoke was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and this is the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of this affair. But if you will ſtill inſiſt upon it, then let the matter be put into equall ballances, and let them ſhew any Church whoſe confeſſion of Faith was ſuch as was obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon you at <hi>Trent:</hi> and if your Religion be <hi>Pius Quartus</hi> his Creed at <hi>Trent,</hi> then we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo have a queſtion to ask, and that is, <hi>Where was your Religion before Trent?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:110472:80"/>
               <p>The Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined that the ſouls departed before the day of Judgment en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Beatificall Viſion. It is certain this Article could not be ſhewn in the Confeſſion of any of the ancient Churches; for moſt of the Fathers were of another opinion. But that which is the greateſt offence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome is not only that theſe doctrines which we ſay are falſe were yet affirmed, but that thoſe things which the Church of God did alwayes reject, or held as Uncertain, ſhould be made Articles of Faith, and ſo become parts of your religion; and of theſe it is that I again ask the queſtion which none of your ſide ſhall ever be able to anſwer for you, Where was your Religion before <hi>Trent?</hi> I
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:110472:80"/>could inſtance in many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; but I ſhall name one to you, which becauſe the thing of it ſelf is of no great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, it will appear the more unreaſonable and intolerable that your Church ſhould adopt it into the things of neceſſary belief, eſpecially ſince it was onely a matter of fact, and they took the falſe part too. For in the 21. Seſſ. Chap. 4. it is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, That <hi>although the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did give the Sacrament of the Euchariſt to Infants, yet they did it without any neceſsity of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> that is, they did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it neceſſary to their ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is notoriouſly falſe, and the contrary is marked out with the black-lead of every man almoſt that reads their Works; and yet your Councel
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:110472:81"/>ſayes this is <hi>ſine controverſiâ cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum;</hi> to be believed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all controverſie: and all Chriſtians forbidden to believe or teach otherwiſe. So that here it is made an Article of Faith amongſt you that a man ſhall neither believe his reaſon nor his eyes: and who can ſhew any confeſſion of Faith in which all the <hi>Trent</hi> doctrine was profeſſed and enjoyned under pain of damnation? <note place="margin">De poteſt. Eccleſ. conſ. 12.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Councel of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> the doctrine touching the Popes power was ſo new, ſo decried, that as <hi>Gerſon</hi> ſayes he hardly ſhould have eſcaped the note of Hereſie that would have ſaid ſo much as was there defined: ſo that in that Article which now makes a great part of your
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:110472:81"/>belief, where was your Religion before the Councel of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance?</hi> and it is notorious that your Councel of <hi>Constance</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the doctrine of the half communion with a <hi>Non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante</hi> to Chriſts inſtitution, that is, with a defiance to it, or a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, obſerved neglect of it, and with a profeſſion it was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the Primitive Church. Where then was your Religion before <hi>John Hus</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> of <hi>Pragues</hi> time, againſt whom that Councel was convened? But by this inſtance it appears moſt certainly that your Church cannot ſhew her confeſſions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after Chriſt, and therefore if we could not ſhew ours immediately before <hi>Luther,</hi> it were not halfe ſo much; for ſince you receded from Chriſts
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:110472:82"/>Doctrine we might well recede from yours; and it matters not who or how many or how long they profeſſed your doctrine, if neither Chriſt nor his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did teach it: ſo that if theſe Articles conſtitute your Church, your Church was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible at the firſt, and if ours was inviſible afterwards it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not; <hi>For yours was inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the dayes of light, and ours was inviſible in the dayes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> For our Church was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes viſible in the reflections of Scripture, and he that had his eyes of faith and reaſon might eaſily have ſeen theſe truths all the way which conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute our Church. But I adde yet farther, that our Church before <hi>Luther</hi> was there where your Church was, in the ſame
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:110472:82"/>place and in the ſame perſons; for divers of the errors which have been amongſt us reformed, were not the conſtituent Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of your Church before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> time; for before the laſt Councels of your Church a man might have been of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion upon eaſier terms; and Indulgences were indeed a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, but no Article of Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your men made it ſo, and that very lately, and ſo were many other things beſides. So that although your men cozen the credulous and the ſimple by calling yours <hi>The old Religion,</hi> yet the difference is vaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Truth and their affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, even as much as between old Errors and new Articles. For although Ignorance and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition had prepared the oare,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:110472:83"/>yet the Councels of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Trent</hi> eſpecially, were the forges and the mint.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if your men had not by all the vile and violent arts of the world ſtopped the mouths of diſſenters, the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion would quickly have been anſwered, or our Articles would have been ſo confeſſed, ſo ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſo publick, that the queſtion could never have been asked; but in deſpite of all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, there were great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of profeſſors who did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and profeſſe and practiſe our doctrines contrary to your Articles; as it is demonſtrated by the Divines of <hi>Germany</hi> in <hi>Illyricus</hi> his <hi>Catalogus teſtium veritatis,</hi> and in Biſhop <hi>Mortons</hi> appeale.</p>
               <p>But with your next objection
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:110472:83"/>you are better pleaſed, and your men make moſt noiſe with it. For you pretend that by our confeſſion ſalvation may be had in your Church; but your men deny it to us; and therefore by the confeſſion of both ſides you may be ſafe, and there is no queſtion concerning you; but of us there is great queſtion, for none but our ſelves ſay that we can be ſaved.</p>
               <p>I anſwer; 1. That ſalvation may be had in your Church, is it ever the truer becauſe we ſay it? If it be not, it can adde no confidence to you, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition gets no ſtrength by our affirmative. But if it be, then our authority is good or elſe our reaſon; and if either be, then we have more reaſon to be believed ſpeaking of our
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:110472:84"/>ſelves; becauſe we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to ſee that our ſelves may be in a ſtate of hope; and therefore we would not venture on this ſide if we had not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reaſon to believe well of our ſelves then of you. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore believe us when it is more likely that we have greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe we have greater concernments, and therefore greater conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As much charity as your men pretend us to ſpeak of you, yet it is a clear caſe our hope of your ſalvation is ſo little that we dare not venture our ſelves on your ſide. The Burger of <hi>Oldwater</hi> being to paſſe a river in his journey to <hi>Daventry,</hi> bad his man try the ford; telling him he hoped he ſhould not be drowned, for though he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:110472:84"/>the River was too deep, ye he thought his horſe would carry him out, or at leaſt, the boats would fetch him off. Such a confidence we may have of you, but you will find that but little warranty, if you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how great an intereſt it is that you venture.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It would be remembred that though the beſt ground of your hope is not the goodneſſe of your own faith, but the greatneſſe of our charity; yet we that charitably hope well of you, have a fulneſſe of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the truth and certainty of our own way; and however you can pleaſe your ſelves with Images of things as having no firm footing for your trifling confidence, yet you can never with your tricks outface us of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:110472:85"/>juſt and firm adherencies; and if you were not empty of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, and greedy of bulruſhes ſnatching at any thing to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port your ſinking cauſe, you would with fear and trembling conſider the direct dangers which we demonſtrate to you to be in your religion rather then flatter your ſelves with collateral, weak, and deceitful hopes of accidental poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that ſome of you may eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If we be more charitable to you then you are to us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in us the beauty and eſſential form of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; be ſure you love as well as make uſe of our charity; but if you make our charity an argument againſt us, remember that you render us evil in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:110472:85"/>change for good; and let it be no brag to you that you have not that charity to us; for therefore the Donatiſts were condemned for Hereticks and Schiſmaticks becauſe they damn'd all the world, and affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no charity to any that was not of their Communion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But that our charity may be ſuch indeed, that is, that it may do you a real benefit, and not turn into Wormwood and Colliquintida, I pray take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in what ſenſe it is that we allow ſalvation may poſſibly be had in your Church. We war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant it not to any, we only hope it for ſome, we allow it to them as to the Sadduces in the Law, and to the Corinthians in the Goſpel who denied the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; that is, till they were
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:110472:86"/>ſufficiently inſtructed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently convinced, and had time and powers to out-wear their prejudices and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes of their education and long perſwaſion. But to them amongſt you who can and do conſider and yet determine for error and intereſt, we have a greater charity, even ſo much as to labour and pray for their converſion, but not ſo much fondneſſe as to flatter them into boldneſſe and pertinacious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herencies to matters of ſo great danger.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But in all this affair though your men are very bold with God and leap into his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat before him, and give wild ſentences concerning the ſalvation of your own party and the damnation of all that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:110472:86"/>yet that which is our charity to you, is indeed the fear of God, and the reverence of his judgments; we do not ſay that all Papiſts are certainly damn'd; we wiſh and deſire vehemently that none of you may periſh; but then this cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of judgment relates not to you, or is derived from any probability which we ſee in your doctrines that differ from ours; but becauſe we know not what rate and value God puts upon the article; It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes neither you nor us to ſay, this or that man ſhall be damn'd for his opinion; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that this is a bold intruſion into that ſecret of God which ſhall not be opened till the day of judgment, and beſides that we know not what allayes and
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:110472:87"/>abatements are to be made by the good meaning &amp; the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the man; all that can concern us is to tell you that you are in error, that you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from Scripture, that you exerciſe tyranny over ſouls, that you leave the Divine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and prevaricate Gods Commandement, that you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Church without truth and without neceſſity, that you tie men to believe things under pain of damnation which cannot be made very probable much leſs certain; and therefore that you ſin againſt God and are in danger of his eternal diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but in giving the finall ſentence as we have no more to do then your men have, yet ſo we refuſe to follow your evil example; and we follow the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:110472:87"/>glorious precedent of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord; who decreed and declared againſt the crime, but not againſt the Criminal before the day. He that does this, or that, is in danger of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, or in danger of judgment, or liable and obnoxious to the danger of hell fire; ſo we ſay of your greateſt errors; they put you in the danger of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing; but that you ſhall or ſhall not periſh, we leave it to your Judge; and if you call this charity, it is well, I am ſure it is plety and the fear of God.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether you may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or whether you ſhall be damned for your errors, does neither depend upon our affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative nor your negative, but according to the rate and value which God ſets upon things.
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:110472:88"/>Whatever we talk, things are as they are, not as we diſpute, or grant, or hope; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were well if your men would leave abuſing you and themſelves with theſe little arts of indirect ſupport. For many men that are warranted, yet do eternally periſh, and you in your Church damne millions who I doubt not ſhall reign with Jeſus eternally in the Heavens.</p>
               <p n="8">8. I wiſh you would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that if any of our men ſay ſalvation may be had in your Church, it is not for the goodneſſe of your new propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, but onely becauſe you doe keep ſo much of that which is our Religion, that upon the confidence of that we hope well concerning you. And we
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:110472:88"/>doe not hope any thing at all that is good of you or your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as it diſtinguiſhes from us and ours: we hope that the good which you have common with us may obtain pardon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly, or may be an antidote of the venome, and an amulet againſt the danger of your very great errors, ſo that if you can derive any confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence from our conceſſion, you muſt remember where it takes root; not upon any thing of yours, but wholly upon the excellency of ours; you are not at all ſafe, or warranted for being Papiſts, but we hope well of ſome of you, for having ſo much of the Proteſtant: and if that wil doe you any good, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in it, and follow it whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever it leads you.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:110472:89"/>
               <p n="9">9. The ſafety that you dream of which we ſay to be on your ſide, is nothing of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance or warranty, but a hope that is collateral, indirect and relative; we doe not ſay any thing whereby you can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude yours to be ſafer then ours, for it is not ſafe at all, but extremely dangerous; we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thoſe errors in themſelves to be damnable, ſome to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in them Impiety, ſome to have Sacrilege, ſome Idolatry, ſome Superſtition, ſome pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices to be conjuring and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and very like to Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, as in your hallowing of Water, and baptizing Bels, and exorcizing Demoniacks; and what ſafety there can be in theſe, or what you can fancy we ſhould allow to you, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:110472:89"/>you need not boaſt of. Now becauſe we hope ſome are ſaved amongſt you, you muſt not conclude yours to be ſafe; for our hope relies upon this. There are many of your propoſitions in which we differ from you, that thouſands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you underſtand and know nothing of, it is to them as if they were not, it is to them now as it was before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, they hear not of it. And though your Prieſts have taken a courſe that the moſt ignorant do practiſe ſome of your abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations moſt groſſely, yet we hope this will not be laid upon them who (as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s expreſſion is) <hi>cautâ ſollicitudine quarunt veritatem, corrigi parati cum invenerint:</hi> do according as they are able warily and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:110472:90"/>ſeek for truth, and are ready to follow it when they find it; men who live good lives, and repent of all their evils known and unknown. Now if we are not deceived in our hopes, theſe men ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the eternall goodneſſe of God which prevailes over the malice of them that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guide you; but if we be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in our hopes of you, your guides have abus'd you, and the blind leaders of the blind will fall together. For,</p>
               <p n="10">10. If you will have the ſecret of this whole affair, this it is. The hopes we have of any of you, (as it is known) princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally relies upon the hopes of your repentance. Now we ſay that a man may repent of an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror which he knowes not of;
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:110472:90"/>as he that prayes heartily for the pardon of all his ſins and errors known and unknown; by his generall repentance may obtain many degrees and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of mercy. Now thus much alſo your men allow to us; theſe who live well, and die in a true though but general repentance of their ſins and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors even amongſt us your beſt and wiſeſt men pronounce to be in a ſaveable condition. Here then we are equal, and we are as ſafe by your confeſſion as you are by ours. But becauſe there are ſome Bigots of your faction fierce and fiery who ſay that a general repentance will not ſerve our turns, but it muſt be a particular renunciation of Proteſtancy; theſe men deny not only to us but to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:110472:91"/>too, all that comfort which they derive from our Conceſſion, and indeed which they can hope for from the mercies of God. For be you ſure we think as ill of your er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors as you can ſuppoſe of our Articles; and therefore if for errors (be they on which ſide it chances) a generall repentance will not ſerve the turn without an actuall dereliction, then flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not your ſelves by any thing of our kindneſſe to your party; for you muſt have a particular if a generall be not ſufficient. But if it be ſufficient for you, it is ſo for us, in caſe we be in error as your men ſuppoſe us; but if it will not ſuffice us for rmedy to thoſe errors you charge us with, neither will it ſuffice you; for the caſe muſt
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:110472:91"/>needs be equall as to the value of repentance and malignity of the error: and therefore theſe men condemn themſelves and will not allow us to hope well of them; but if they will allow us to hope, it muſt be by affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the value of a generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and if they allow that, they muſt hope as well of ours as we of theirs: but if they deny it to us, they deny it to themſelves, and then they can no more brag of any thing of our conceſſion. This onely I adde to this conſideration; that your men doe not, cannot charge upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us any doctrine that is in its matter and effect im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious; there is nothing poſitive in our doctrine, but is either true or innocent, but we are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd for denying your ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructures:
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:110472:92"/>ours therefore (if we be deceived) is but like a ſin of omiſſion; yours are ſins of commiſſion in caſe you are in the wrong (as we believe you to be) and therefore you muſt needs be in the greater danger then we can be ſuppoſed, by how much ſins of omiſſion are leſſe then ſins of commiſſion.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Your very way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from your charity is a very fallacy and a trick that muſt needs deceive you if you rely upon it. For whereas your men argue thus: The Proteſtants ſay we Papiſts may be ſaved; and ſo ſay we too: but we Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſay that you Proteſtants cannot, therefore it is ſafeſt to be a Papiſt; conſider that of this argument if it ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, any bold heretick can
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:110472:92"/>make uſe, againſt any modeſt Chriſtian of a true perſwaſion. For, if he can but out-face the modeſty of the good man, and tell him he ſhall be damn'd; unleſſe that modeſt man ſay as much of him, you ſee impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhal get the better of the day. But it is thus in every er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. Fifteen Biſhops of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> in immediate ſucceſſion were circumciſed, believing it to be neceſſary ſo to be: with theſe other Chriſtian Churches who were of the uncircumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did communicate: Suppoſe now that theſe Biſhops had not onely thought it neceſſary for themſelves but for others too; this argument you ſee was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: you of the uncircumciſion who doe communicate with us, think that we may be ſaved
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:110472:93"/>though we are circumciſed, but we doe not think that you who are not circumciſed can be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, therefore it is the ſafeſt way to be circumciſed: I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you would not have thought their argument good, neither would you have had your children circumciſed. But this argument may ſerve the Presbyterians as well as the Papiſts. We are indeed very kind to them in our ſentences concerning their ſalvation; and they are many of them as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to us; If they ſhould ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue ſo as you doe, and ſay, you Epiſcopall men think we Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians though in errors can be ſaved, and we ſay ſo too: but we think you Epiſcopal men are Enemies of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Jeſus Chriſt; and
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:110472:93"/>therefore we think you in a damnable condition, therefore it is ſafer to be a Presbyterian; I know not what your men would think of the argument in their hands, I am ſure we had reaſon to complain that we are uſed very ill on both hands for no other cauſe but becauſe we are charitable. But it is not our caſe alone; but the old Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks were uſed juſt ſo by the Donatiſts in this very argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as we are uſed hy your men. The Donatiſts were ſo fierce againſt the Catholicks, that they would re-baptize all them who came to their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches from the other: But the Catholicks, as knowing the Donatiſts did give right Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, admitted their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts to Repentance, but did
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:110472:94"/>not re-baptize them. Upon this ſcore, the Donatiſts triumphed, ſaying, You Catholicks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our Baptiſme to be good, and ſo ſay we: But we Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts deny your Baptiſme to be good; therefore it is ſafer to be of our ſide then yours. Now what ſhould the Catholicks ſay or doe? Should they lie for God and for Religion, and to ſerve the ends of Truth ſay the Donatiſts Baptiſme was not good? That they ought not. Should they damne all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts, and make the rent wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? It was too great already. What then? They were quiet, and knew that the Donatiſts ſought advantages by their own fierceneſſe, and trampled upon the others charity; but ſo they hardened themſelves in error,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:110472:94"/>and became evill, becauſe the others were good.</p>
               <p>I ſhall trouble you no further now, but deſire you to conſider of theſe things with as much caution, as they were written with charity.</p>
               <p>Till I hear from you, I ſhall pray to God to open your heart and your underſtanding, that you may return from whence you are fallen, and repent, and do your firſt work. Which that you may doe, is the hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your very affectionate Friend and Servant, JER: TAYLOR.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:110472:95"/>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:110472:95"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Second Letter: Written to a Perſon newly converted to the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Bleſſe GOD I am ſafely ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived where I deſired to be after my unwilling depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from the place of your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode and danger: And now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I can have no other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of my tenderneſſe, I account that I have a treble Obligation to ſignifie it by my care of your biggeſt and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:110472:96"/>intereſt. And becauſe it hath pleaſed God to make me an Inſtrument of making you to underſtand in ſome fair mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the excellencies of a true and holy Religion, and that I have pointed out ſuch follies and errours in the Roman Church, at which your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding being forward and pregnant, did of it ſelf ſtart as at imperfect ill-looking Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, give me leave to doe that now which is the purpoſe of my Charity, that is, teach you to turn this to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a holy life, that you may not only be changed but converted. For the Church of <hi>England</hi> whither you are now come is not in condition to boaſt her ſelf in the reputation of changing the opinion of a
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:110472:96"/>ſingle perſon, though never ſo excellent; She hath no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ends to ſerve which muſt ſtand upon fame and noiſes; all that ſhe can deſign, is to ſerve God, to advance the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Lord, and the good of ſouls, and to rejoyce in the Croſſe of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Therefore I deſire you to remember that as now you are taught to pray both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and privately, in a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage underſtood, ſo it is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded your affections ſhould be forward, in proportion to the advantages which your prayer hath in the underſtanding part. For though you have been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten told and have heard, that ignorance is the Mother of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, you will find that the propoſition is unnaturall and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:110472:97"/>common ſenſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; becauſe it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deſire that of which we know nothing, unleſſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it ſelf be fantaſticall and illuſive: it is neceſſary that in the ſame proportion in which we underſtand any good thing, in the ſame we ſhall alſo deſire it, and the more particular and minute your notices are, the more paſſionate and materiall alſo your affections will be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it; and if they be good things for which we are taught to pray, the more you know them the more reaſon you have to love them; It is monſtrous to think that devotion, that is, paſſionate deſires of religious things, and the earneſt proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of them ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by any thing of ignorance
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:110472:97"/>or leſs perfect notices in any ſenſe. Since therefore you are taught to pray, ſo that your underſtanding is the praecentor or the Maſter of the Quire, and you know what you ſay; your deſires are made humane, religious, expreſſe, materiall (for theſe are the advantages of prayers and Liturgies well underſtood) be pleaſed alſo to remember, that now if you be not alſo paſſionate and devout for the things you mention, you will want the Spirit of prayer, and be more inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then before. In many of your prayers before (eſpecially the publique) you heard a voice but ſaw and perceived nothing of the ſenſe, and what you underſtood of it was like the man in the Goſpel that was
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:110472:98"/>half blind, he ſaw men walking like Trees, and ſo you poſſibly might perceive the meaning of it in generall; You knew when they came to the Epiſtle, when to the Goſpel, when the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troit, when the <hi>Pax,</hi> when any of the other more generall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods were; but you could have nothing of the Spirit of prayer, that is, nothing of the devotion and the holy affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the particular excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which could or ought there to have been repreſented, but now you are taught how you may be really devout, it is made facil and eaſie, and there can want nothing but your conſent and obſervation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas now you are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off from all humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidences, from relying wholly
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:110472:98"/>and almoſt ultimately upon the Prieſts power and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall act, from reckoning pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by numbers, from forms and out-ſides, you are not to think that the Prieſts power is leſſe, that the Sacraments are not effective, that your prayers may not be repeated frequently; but you are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that all outward things and Ceremonies, all Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and Inſtitutions work their effect in the vertue of Chriſt, by ſome morall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument; The Prieſts in the Church of <hi>England</hi> can abſolve you as much as the Roman Prieſts could fairly pretend; but then we teach that you muſt firſt be a penitent and a returning perſon, and our ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution does but manifeſt the
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:110472:99"/>work of God, and comfort and inſtruct your Conſcience, direct and manage it; You ſhall be abſolved here, but not unleſſe you live an holy life; So that in this you will find no change but to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a ſtrict life; we will not flatter you and cozen your dear ſoul by pretended mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteries, but we ſo order our diſcourſes and directions that all our miniſtrations may be really effective, and when you receive the holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt, or the Lords Supper, it does more good here then they doe there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if they conſecrate ritely, yet they doe not communicate you fully; and if they offer the whole repreſentative Sacrifice, yet they doe not give you the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:110472:99"/>whole Sacrament; onely we enjoyn that you come with ſo much holineſſe, that the grace of God in your heart may be the principall, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in our hands may be the miniſtring and aſſiſting part: we doe not promiſe great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects to eaſie trifling diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe we would not deceive, but really procure to you great effects; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you are now to come to our offices with the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations as before, of pardon, of grace, of ſanctification; but you muſt doe ſomething more of the work your ſelf, that we may not doe leſſe in effect then you have in your expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; We will not to advance the reputation of our power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you into a leſs bleſſing.</p>
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:110472:100"/>
               <p n="3">3. Be carefull that you doe not flatter your ſelf, that in our Communion you may have more eaſe and liberty of life; for though I know your pious ſoul deſires paſſionately to pleaſe God and to live religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, yet I ought to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to prevent a temptation, leſt it at any time ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe your ſeverity: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as to confeſſion to a Prieſt (which how it is uſually practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongſt the Roman party, your ſelf can very well account, and you have complain'd ſadly, that it is made an ordinary act, eaſie and tranſient, ſometime matter of temptation, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times impertinent, but) ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it free from ſuch ſcandall to which ſome mens folly did betray it, yet the ſame ſeverity
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:110472:100"/>you'l find among us; for though we will not tell a lye to help a ſinner, and ſay that is neceſſary which is only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to make men doe themſelves good, yet we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and commend it, and doe all the work of ſouls to all thoſe people that will be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by all means; to deout perſons, that make Religion the buſineſſe of their lives, and they that doe not ſo in the Churches of the Roman Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, as they find but little advantage by peroidical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, ſo they feel but little awfulneſſe and ſeverity by the injunction; you muſt confeſſe to God all your ſecret actions, you muſt adviſe with a holy man in all the affairs of your ſoul, you will be but an ill
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:110472:101"/>friend to your ſelf if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale from him the ſtate of your ſpirituall affairs: We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not to hear the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of every ſinne, but when matter of juſtice is concerned, or the nature of the ſinne is changed, that is, when it ought to be made a Queſtion; and you will find that though the Church of <hi>England</hi> gives you much liberty from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of innumerable Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and humane devices, yet in the matter of holineſſe you will be tied to very great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but ſuch a ſervice as is perfect freedome, that is, the ſervice of God and the love of the holy Jeſus, and a very ſtrict religious life; for we doe not promiſe heaven, but upon the ſame terms it is promiſed us,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:110472:101"/>that is, <hi>Repentance towards God and Faith in our Lord Jeſus:</hi> and as in faith we make no more to be neceſſary then what is made ſo in holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, ſo in the matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance we give you no eaſie devices, and ſuffer no leſſening definitions of it, but oblige you to that ſtrictneſſe which is the condition of being ſaved, and ſo expreſſed to be by the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Word of God; but ſuch as in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> they doe not ſo much ſtand upon.</p>
               <p>Madam, I am weary of my Journey, and although I did purpoſe to have ſpoken many things more, yet I deſire that my not doing it may be laid upon the account of my weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:110472:102"/>all that I ſhall adde to the maine buſineſſe is this.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Read the Scripture dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, and with an humble ſpirit, and in it obſerve what is plain, and believe and live accordingly. Trouble not your ſelf with what is difficult, for in that your duty is not deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Pray frequently and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually; I had rather your prayers ſhould be often then long. It was well ſaid of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch, Magno verborum fraeno uti decet cum ſuperiore colloquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi> When you ſpeak to your ſuperiour you ought to have a bridle upon your tongue, much more when you ſpeak to God. I ſpeak of what is decent in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our ſelves and our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:110472:102"/>diſtances from God: but if love makes you ſpeak, ſpeak on, ſo ſhall your prayers be full of charity and devotion, <hi>Nullus est amore ſuperior, ille te coget ad veniam, qui me ad multilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium;</hi> Love makes God to be our friend, and our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches more united and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable; and therefore you may ſay to God, <hi>the ſame love which made me ſpeak, will alſo move thee to hear and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi> Love and devotion may enlarge your Letanies, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe can, unleſſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity does interpoſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Be curious not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate but with the true Sonnes of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> leſt if you follow them that were amongſt us, but
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:110472:103"/>are gone out from us, becauſe they were not of us) you be offended and tempted to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute their follies to the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Trouble your ſelf with no controverſies willingly, but how you may beſt pleaſe God by a ſtrict and ſevere converſation.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If any Proteſtant live looſely, remember that he diſhonours an excellent Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and that it may be no more laid upon the charge of our Church, then the ill lives of moſt Chriſtians may upon the whole Religion.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Let no man or woman affright you with declamations and ſcaring words of <hi>Heretick,</hi> and <hi>Damnation,</hi> and <hi>Changeable;</hi>
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:110472:103"/>for theſe words may be ſpoken againſt them that return to light, as well as to thoſe that goe to darkneſſe, and that which men of all ſides can ſay, it can be of effect to no ſide upon its own ſtrength or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion.</p>
               <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb facs="tcp:110472:104"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:110472:104"/>
               <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF you ſhall think it fit that theſe papers paſse further then your own eye and Cloſet, I deſire they may be conſig'nd into the hands of my worthy friend Dr. <hi>Wedderburne:</hi> For I doe not only expoſe all my ſickneſſe to his cure, but I ſubmit my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſses to his cenſure, being as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident to find of him charity for what is pardonable, as remedy for what is curable: but indeed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam I look upon that worthy man as an <hi>Idea</hi> of friendſhip, and if I had no other notices of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or converſation to inſtruct me then his, it were ſufficient: For
<pb facs="tcp:110472:105"/>whatſoever I can ſay of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, I can ſay of his, and as all that know him reckon him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the beſt Phyſicians, ſo I knew him worthy to be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the beſt friends.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:110472:105"/>
            <head>A <hi>Catalogue</hi> of ſome Books Printed for <hi>R. Royſton</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Ivie-lane,</hi> London.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. Books written by <hi>H Hammond,</hi> D.D.</head>
               <p>A Paraphraſe and Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon all the Books of the New Teſt. in <hi>fol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Practical Catechiſme,</hi> with other Engliſh Treatiſes of the ſame Author, in two vol. 4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Diſſertationes quatuor, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Epiſcopatûs Jura ex S. Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturis &amp; Primaeva Antiquitate adſtruuntur, contra ſententiam D.</hi> Blondelii <hi>&amp; aliorum.</hi> in 4.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A Letter of Reſolution of ſix Queries. in 12.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Of Schiſme. A Defence of the Church of <hi>Engl.</hi> againſt the Exceptions of the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts. in 12.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:110472:106"/>
               <p n="6">6. Of Fundamentals in a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion referring to practice. in 12.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Paraeneſis,</hi> or ſeaſonable exhortatory to all true ſons of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> in 12.</p>
               <p n="8">8. A Collection of ſeveral Replies and Vindications, moſt of them in defence of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in three Volumes in 4.</p>
               <p n="9">9. A Review of the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe and Annotations on all the Books of the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> with ſome additions and alterations, in 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:110472:106"/>
               <head>II. Books and Sermons written by <hi>Jer: Taylor,</hi> D.D. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, A Courſe of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons for all the Sundayes of the Year; together with a Diſcourſe of the Divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, Neceſſity, Sacredneſſe and Separation of the Office Miniſteriall, in <hi>fol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Hiſtory of the Life and Death of the Ever-bleſſed Jeſus Chriſt, ſecond Edition, in <hi>fol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Rule and Exerciſes of Holy Living, in 12.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Rule and Exerciſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Holy Dying, in 12.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Golden Grove, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> A Manual of daily Prayers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:110472:107"/>to the dayes of the Week, together with a ſhort method of Peace and Holineſſe, in 12.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Doctrine and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Repentance reſcued from Popular Errours, in a large 8. Newly publiſhed.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A Collection of Polemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Moral Diſcourſes, in <hi>fol.</hi> Newly publiſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Myſterie of Jeſuitiſme, diſcovered in certain Letters, Written upon occaſion of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent differences at</hi> Sorbonne, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the</hi> Janſeniſts <hi>and the</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liniſts. <hi>New.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:110472:107"/>
               <head>III. Books written by M. <hi>Th: Pierce,</hi> Rector of <hi>Brington.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THe <hi>Sinner Impleaded</hi> in his own <hi>Court,</hi> wherein are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the great diſcouragements from Sinning, which the Sinner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth from Sin it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Correct Copy of ſome Notes concernig Gods Decrees, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of Reprobation. The 2. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Now at the Preſſe with ſome Additionals.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Divine <hi>Philanthropie</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Divine Verity defended.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
